THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC
FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD, INDIVISIBLE, WITH
LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WOULD LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT US OF GROVE TV TODAY
THAT IS ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE TRANSCRIPTS
AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE HERE IN THE BOARD'S
LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER IN ROOM TWO 52ND FLOOR OF CITY HALL.
AND WHEN YOU ARE NOT ABLE TO BE HERE, THE PROCEEDINGS ARE
AIRING LIVE ON SRF GEO TV'S LOCAL CABLE CHANNEL OR YOU CAN
CATCH THE LIVE STREAMING AT S.F. GEO VTV DOT ORG.
>> IF YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING YOU
MAY DO SO BY SENDING IT VIA EMAIL.
JUST SEND IT TO BE OFFSET AS IF GOV TALK OR USE THE POSTAL
SERVICE AND ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B
GOODLATTE PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA
94102. IF YOU'D LIKE TO MAKE A
REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE
AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE
ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS
DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. MEMBERS.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. AS WE HAVE DONE BEFORE, I THINK
WE ARE GOING TO BE RECUSING SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR ONE MORE
MEETING. I UNDERSTAND THAT SHE IS GOING
TO BE BACK IN THE BUILDING ON MONDAY.
BUT FOR NOW COULD I HAVE A MOTION EXCUSED SUPERVISOR
FIELDER MOVED BY CHEN SECONDED BY DORSEY.
COLLEAGUES, CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION?
WITHOUT OBJECTION. SUPERVISOR FIELDER IS EXCUSED.
>> AND THEN QUICK LET'S GO TO OUR APPROVAL OF MEETING
MINUTES. YES.
THE APPROVAL OF THE MAY 19TH 2026 BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
>> COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN SECONDED BY CHERYL.
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED? SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR MENDELSON HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR FOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG
I'M SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS
PLEASE CALL ITEMS ONE AND TWO TOGETHER.
>> ITEM ONE IS THE PROPOSED INTERIM BUDGET
AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE ALL ESTIMATED
RECEIPTS AND EXPENDITURES FOR DEPARTMENTS OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY AS OF MAY 30TH 2026 FOR FISCAL YEAR ENDING JUNE
30TH 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028 AND ITEM TWO IS THE PROPOSED
INTERIM ANNUAL SALARY ORDINANCE TO ENUMERATE POSITIONS IN THE
ANNUAL BUDGET AND THE APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE FOR
FISCAL YEAR ENDING JUNE 30TH, 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028.
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THESE ITEMS ON ITEMS ONE AND TWO
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR
HI HIGH MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WILTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I'M SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY
AND DORSEY I THEIR ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
THREE ITEM THREE IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE CODE TO PROHIBIT THE SALE OFFER AND DELIVERY OF
LITHIUM LITHIUM ION BATTERIES AND REPLACEMENT LITHIUM ION
BATTERIES THAT DO NOT MEET SPECIFIED CERTIFICATION
REQUIREMENTS TO ANY ADDRESS WITHIN SAN FRANCISCO TO
ESTABLISH ENFORCEMENT PROCESSES AND PENALTIES FOR VIOLATIONS TO
AUTHORIZE THE CITY ATTORNEY TO SEEK INJUNCTIVE AND MONETARY
RELIEF AND ATTORNEY'S FEES AND TO AUTHORIZE THE FIRE
DEPARTMENT TO IMPLEMENT THE RESTRICTION THROUGH RULES,
FORMS AND GUIDANCE. COLLEAGUES, I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED AND PLEASE CALL ITEM FOUR.
>> ITEM FOUR. THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
DIVISION ONE OF THE TRANSPORTATION CODE TO MAKE NON
SUBSTANTIVE ORGANIZATIONAL CHANGES TO THE PROVISIONS
GOVERNING THE INTERDEPARTMENTAL STAFF COUNCIL ON TRAFFIC
AND TRANSPORTATION AND TO REMOVE OUTDATED PROVISIONS
CONCERNING THE TEMPORARY USE OF STREETS FOR SCHOOL USES TO
AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE AND FIRE CODES TO UPDATE
CROSS-REFERENCES AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION
AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW
BUSINESS. >> PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER FIVE
ITEM FIVE THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY APPROVE AN
AMENDED AND RESTATED LEASE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY
AND COUNTY AND TANS INC FOR THE RETAIL SPACE LOCATED AT 44
ALLEN STREET IN THE EL PASO FERAL GARAGE TO AMEND THE
CALCULATION OF THE MONTHLY BASE RENT TO A PERCENTAGE RENT
CALCULATED AS 8% OF GROSS REVENUES RETROACTIVE TO JANUARY
FIRST 2021 TO AMEND THE MONTHLY WATER CHARGE TO APPROXIMATELY
2400 TO RETRO ACTIVE TO FEBRUARY 1ST 2024 TO AMEND THE
CALCULATION OF BASE RENT AND WATER CHARGE DURING THE
FIRST OPTION TO EXTEND TO REQUIRE TAD'S TO PAY A $4,000
ADMINISTRATIVE FEE TO IMPOSE MINIMUM HOURS OF OPERATION TO
WAIVE TAX OBLIGATION TO PAY BEST BASE RENT FOR THE TERM
BEGINNING APRIL 1ST 2020 TO DECEMBER 31ST 2020 AND TO WAIVE
TOWN'S OBLIGATION TO PAY OUTSTANDING WATER CHARGE
BEGINNING FEBRUARY 1ST, 2020 TO JANUARY 31ST 2024 EFFECTIVE
UPON APPROVAL OF THE RESOLUTION THROUGH THE EXPIRATION DATE OF
APRIL 30TH 2029 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL OUT A NUMBER SIX
ITEM SIX THIS IS A MOTION ENACTING A 4.50% COST OF LIVING
ADJUSTMENT TO THE BASE FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 26 CONTRACT
AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 3.4 MILLION FOR BUDGET
AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST SERVICES EFFECTUATED AS OF JULY
1ST 2026 TO RESULT IN A NEW FISCAL YEAR 2026 THROUGH 27
CONTRACT AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 3.5 MILLION AN
ANNUAL INCREASE OF 152,000 AND A TOTAL NOT TO EXCEED
CONTRACT AMOUNT OF 36 MILLION FOR THE CONTRACT TERM ENDING
DECEMBER 31ST 2031 AND TO DIRECT THE CLERK TO TAKE THE
ADMINISTRATIVE ACTIONS ACCORDINGLY.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. >> MADAME CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER SEVEN. ITEM SEVEN THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO ADD THE COMMEMORATIVE STREET NAME TONI STEPHANIE WAY TO
FALMOUTH STREET BETWEEN FOLSOM STREET AND SHIPLEY STREET
IN RECOGNITION OF RETIRED SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT
CAPTAIN TONY STEPHANIE. >> AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER EIGHT ITEM EIGHT THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATE OF CODE TO CHANGE
THE NAME OF THIS STATUS SO WOMEN'S DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
PROGRAM FUND TO THE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE SHELTER BASED PROGRAM
FUND TO REVISE THE PURPOSE OF THE FUND TO ESTABLISH THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT OR
ANOTHER AGENCY DESIGNATED BY THE MAYOR AS ADMINISTRATOR OF
THE FUND WITH DELEGATED DUTIES AND TO UPDATE PROVISIONS
REGARDING THE FUND TO REFLECT STATE LAW CHANGES RELATING TO
FEES COLLECTED BY THE COUNTY CLERK FOR THE FUND.
>> COLLEAGUES YOUR OFFICES SHOULD HAVE RECEIVED AND YOU
SHOULD HAVE AT YOUR DESKS RIGHT NOW A PROPOSED NON SUBSTANTIVE
CLARIFYING AMENDMENT. ITEM EIGHT IS AN ORDINANCE AS
OUR CLERK INDICATED, UPDATING SECTIONS OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE GOVERNING DOMESTIC VIOLENCE SHELTER BASED
GOVERNING THE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE SHELTER BASE PROGRAM FUND.
AFTER THIS ITEM WAS HEARD AND RULES COMMITTEE ON JUNE
15TH, THE COUNTY CLERK ALERTED US TO A PHRASE THAT COULD
CREATE CONFUSION SPECIFICALLY ON PAGE TWO LINES TEN AND 11
THE PROPOSED ORDINANCE CURRENTLY STATES OR AT LEAST AS
IT APPEARS IN THE AGENDA STATES THAT IN ACCORDANCE WITH STATE
LAW $23 SHOULD BE COLLECTED EITHER AT THE ISSUANCE OF A
MARRIAGE LICENSE OR AT THE FILING OF A CERTIFICATE OF
MARRIAGE AND THEN DEPOSITED INTO THE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
SHELTER BASE PROGRAM FUND. THE COUNTY CLERK HAS POINTED
OUT THAT THERE IS NO SPECIFIC LEGAL PROCESS OR FEE ASSOCIATED
WITH FILING A CERTIFICATE OF MARRIAGE AND THEREFORE AT THE
RECOMMENDATION OF THE CLERK WE HAVE NEW LANGUAGE AND AN
AMENDMENT TO STRIKE OUT THE PHRASE OR AT THE TIME OF THE
FILING OF ANY CERTIFICATE OF MARRIAGE.
ON PAGE TWO, LINE 11 CLARIFYING THAT THE $23 WILL BE COLLECTED
AT THE TIME OF ISSUANCE OF A MARRIAGE LICENSE.
THE CITY ATTORNEY HAS CONFIRMED THAT THIS IS A NON SUBSTANTIVE
AMENDMENT. THANK YOU FOR THAT.
AND SO I'M GOING TO NOW MAKE A MOTION TO AMEND ITEM NUMBER
EIGHT FILE 250720 TO STRIKE OUT THE PHRASE OR AT THE TIME OF
THE FILING OF ANY CERTIFICATE OF MARRIAGE.
AND ON PAGE TWO, LINE 11 AS I JUST DESCRIBED COULD I HAVE A
SECOND SECONDED BY CHERYL AND COLLEAGUES IF THERE ARE NO
OBJECTIONS WE'LL TAKE THAT AMENDMENT WITHOUT OBJECTION.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
AND ON THE AMENDED ITEM I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT SAME HOUSE
SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE AMENDED
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM NUMBER NINE. >> ITEM NINE THIS IS A MOTION
TO APPOINT ATHENA BING YING ANG AND RAYMOND DANG.
>> TERMS ENDING JANUARY 1ST 2027 TO THE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
COUNCIL TERM ENDING JANUARY 1ST 2020 EIGHT.
>> COLLEAGUES LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER TEN. >> ITEM TEN THIS IS A MOTION TO
REAPPOINT MARIA DAVIS TO THE ENTERTAINMENT COMMISSION TERM
ENDING JULY 1ST 2030. >> AGAIN, SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION
IS APPROVED. >> MADAM CLERK, WE HAVE A
COMMITTEE REPORT I BELIEVE. YES.
ITEM 11 IT WAS CONSIDERED BY THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A
RESCHEDULED MEETING ON MONDAY JUNE 22ND AND WAS FORWARDED AS
A COMMITTEE REPORT. ITEM 11 IS A RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF
HOUSING'S EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR, ITS CHIEF DEPUTIES AND DEPUTY
DIRECTORS AND PROGRAM DIRECTORS TO SOLICIT DONATIONS FROM
VARIOUS PRIVATE ENTERPRISE ENTITIES AND ORGANIZATIONS TO
SUPPORT THE EXPANSION OF TEMPORARY SHELTER AND OTHER
HOMELESS SERVICES TO SUPPORT PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS NOTWITHSTANDING THE BE HAS TO PAYMENT ORDINANCE
AND WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL.
YES SUPERVISOR MAHMUD YOUR FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW
BUSINESS SUBMIT THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR MENDELSOHN MR.
PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM. I'M ASKING THAT WE ADJOURN
TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF JOHN V GIUSTI.
BELOVED SON, HUSBAND, COUSIN, FRIEND AND BUSINESS PARTNER OF
MASOOD SAMIRA AT ARIA PROPERTIES WHO DIED ON JUNE
7TH, 2026 AT THE AGE OF 80. >> JOHN WAS A PROUD LIFELONG
SAN FRANCISCAN BORN TO JOHN B GIUSTI AND ANNA BUNDER GIUSTI
WHOSE LOVE, VALUES AND EXAMPLE REMAINED A GUIDING INFLUENCE
THROUGHOUT HIS LIFE. AFTER GRADUATING FROM BALBO
HIGH SCHOOL HE WENT ON TO EARN A BACHELOR OF SCIENCE
IN PRINTING FROM CALIFORNIA POLYTECHNIC STATE UNIVERSITY
SAN LUIS OBISPO. HE SERVED AS A COMMISSIONED
OFFICER IN THE ARMY AND WAS AWARDED THE BRONZE STAR MEDAL
IN RECOGNITION OF HIS COURAGE AND DEDICATION.
A VIETNAM VETERAN, HE OFTEN SPOKE OF HIS MILITARY SERVICE
WITH PRIDE EVEN AFTER COMPLETING ACTIVE DUTY, HE
CONTINUED HIS SERVICE AS A RESERVE COMMISSIONED OFFICER.
FOLLOWING HIS MILITARY SERVICE, HE WORKED FOR MORE THAN TWO
DECADES AT BONE OF THE SAN BONE OF SAN FRANCISCO, A FINANCIAL
PRINTING COMPANY WHERE HE CONTRIBUTED TO MAJOR INITIAL
PUBLIC OFFERINGS AND ANNUAL REPORTS FOR NUMEROUS FORTUNE
500 COMPANIES. EVENTUALLY HE MOVED FROM
FINANCIAL PRINTING TO A CAREER IN REAL ESTATE WHERE HE FOUND A
NATURAL OUTLET FOR HIS ENTREPRENEURIAL SPIRIT
AND PASSION FOR HELPING OTHERS. UNDER THE MENTORSHIP OF ROBERT
SCHUMANN, HE JOINED HARTFORD PROPERTIES AND BUILT A
SUCCESSFUL CAREER BEFORE TEAMING UP WITH MASOOD SAMARI
TO FOUND ARIA PROPERTIES IN 2012.
JOHN LOVED REAL ESTATE BECAUSE IT GAVE HIM THE OPPORTUNITY TO
BUILD RELATIONSHIPS AND HELP OTHERS ACHIEVE THEIR GOALS.
HE WILL BE REMEMBERED FOR HIS KINDNESS, GENEROSITY AND SENSE
OF HUMOR. HE ALWAYS HAD A STORY TO SHARE
A PERSPECTIVE TO OFFER AND A WAY OF MAKING THOSE AROUND HIM
FEEL WELCOME. AND IT IS HE FOUND GREAT JOY
IN SPENDING TIME WITH FAMILY AND FRIENDS TRAVELING
AND GATHERING PEOPLE TOGETHER AROUND GOOD FOOD AND GOOD
COMPANY. HE HAD A SPECIAL PLACE IN HIS
HEART FOR HIS BELOVED BEAGLES GINGER ONE, GINGER TWO
AND DOLLY WHOM HE ADORED AND CARED FOR WITH ENDLESS
AFFECTION. HE IS LOVINGLY REMEMBERED BY
HIS PARTNER JOSEPH J. JR, HIS NEPHEWS DENNIS WALLS
AND JOHN HOLDS HIS GRANDNEPHEWS DONALD AND DAVE AND DANIEL
HALLS HIS COUSIN DONALD BONDER ALFONSO AL BONDER VIENNA BONDER
AND JOHANNA VANDER KRON AS WELL AS HIS LONGTIME BUSINESS
PARTNER MASOOD. SUMMARY AND MASOOD'S WIFE FATTY
TABRIZI. JOHN'S LIFE WAS DEFINED BY
SERVICE, FRIENDSHIP, LAUGHTER AND LOVE.
HE LEAVES BEHIND A LASTING LEGACY IN THE LIVES HE TOUCHED
AND HE WILL BE DEEPLY MISSED BY ALL WHO KNEW HIM.
REST AND REST IN PEACE JOHN GIUSTI.
>> MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING AND THE REST I SUBMIT
. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES, I WOULD LIKE TO CLOSE TODAY'S MEETING ON BEHALF
OF THE WHOLE BOARD. IN LOVING MEMORY OF JULIE
DRISCOLL FERRER THE BELOVED MOTHER OF OUR DEAR FRIEND
AND COLLEAGUE DISTRICT SEVEN LEGISLATIVE AIDE MICHAEL FERRER
JR. JULIE WAS A PROUD FOURTH
GENERATION SAN FRANCISCAN AND THE ELDEST OF SEVEN
DRISCOLL CHILDREN OF MICHAEL JOSEPH DRISCOLL AND REGINA
ESTELLE BAKER DRISCOLL. SHE ATTENDED SAINT MARY'S
ELEMENTARY SCHOOL AND MERCY HIGH SCHOOL RECEIVED HER
UNDERGRADUATE DEGREE FROM SEATTLE UNIVERSITY AND EARNED A
JURIS DOCTORATE FROM GOLDEN GATE UNIVERSITY SCHOOL OF LAW.
AT THE AGE OF 43, JULIE WAS A GIFTED ELEMENTARY SCHOOL
TEACHER AND SPENT 20 YEARS TEACHING AT VARIOUS SCHOOLS
IN THE CITY INCLUDING SAINT BRENDAN SCHOOL.
AND AS AN AVID READER. SHE JOYFULLY INSTILLED IN HER
STUDENTS AND CHILDREN A LIFELONG LOVE OF BOOKS JOLIE'S
COURAGEOUS ENDEAVOR TO RETURN TO LAW SCHOOL MID-CAREER WAS
ONE OF THE MANY EXAMPLES OF HER INDOMITABLE SPIRIT STRENGTH OF
CHARACTER AND INCREDIBLE PERSEVERANCE.
SHE HAD A SHARP AND BRILLIANT MIND AND DID NOT LET CONVENTION
DICTATE HER CHOICES. >> SHE SERVED AS AN INSPIRATION
PROVING BY EXAMPLE THAT WITH DETERMINATION, DISCIPLINE,
INTELLECT AND AN UNWAVERING WORK ETHIC YOU CAN FOLLOW YOUR
DREAMS AT ANY AGE AND ACHIEVE GREAT SUCCESS.
JULIE HAD A DISTINGUISHED CAREER AS AN EQUITY PARTNER AT
THE FIRM ERICKSON ANN ARBOR'S NOT AND PRACTICED GENERAL CIVIL
LITIGATION FOR 23 YEARS UNTIL HER RETIREMENT IN 2011.
THROUGHOUT HER LIFE PEOPLE WERE DRAWN TO HER FOR HER WISE
COUNSEL ABILITY TO LISTEN WITHOUT JUDGMENT AND FOR HER
WARM OPEN HEART. JULIE WAS KNOWN FOR HER
KINDNESS, STRENGTH AND HER JOYFUL LAUGH THAT WOULD WARM UP
ANYONE SHE MET AND SHE IS ALSO REMEMBERED FOR HER LIFELONG
COMMITMENT TO SERVICE. AMONG HER MANY COMMUNITY
CONTRIBUTIONS SHE SERVED ON THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS FOR LITTLE
CHILDREN'S AID AND REARDON HIGH SCHOOL.
SHE DEVOTED COUNTLESS HOURS TO ST BRENDAN'S SCHOOL AND AS A
MEMBER OF QUEEN'S BENCH BAR ASSOCIATION WHICH IS COMMITTED
TO EMPOWERING WOMEN AND PROMOTING GENDER EQUITY.
GIVEN ALL OF HER ACHIEVEMENTS, JULIE'S GREATEST LEGACY WHERE
SHE TRULY SHONE BRIGHTEST WAS HER DEDICATION TO HER FAMILY.
AS A MOTHER, SISTER, AUNT, WIFE AND GRANDMOTHER, THE MOST
SIGNIFICANT STORY OF JULIE'S LIFE WAS THAT WAS THAT OF THE
LOVE SHE SHARED WITH HER LATE HUSBAND MICHAEL FARRAH SENIOR.
THEIR MARRIAGE WAS A TRIBUTE TO COMMITMENT, FRIENDSHIP
AND FAMILY. SHE WAS A WONDERFUL MOTHER TO
MICHAEL FARRAH JUNIOR AND FARRAH SARIAH FARRAH
DAUGHTER IN LAW MIA MY EDRIS AND FARRAH IN HER LATE SON
GEORGE FARRAH THE THIRD HER GRANDCHILDREN FINNEGAN, ELIJAH
AND JULIANNE WERE THE LIGHT OF HER LIFE WITH WHOM SHE SHARED A
JOYFUL AND UNCONDITIONALLY LOVING RELATIONSHIP.
JULIE WAS A SPIRITUAL WOMAN WITH A STRONG FAITH.
SHE WAS A GUIDING LIGHT, A SHINING EXAMPLE OF HOW TO LIVE
GRACEFULLY AS A MATRIARCH OF A LARGE EXTENDED FAMILY.
JULIE WILL BE MISSED BY MANY. TO MIKE AND SORAYA AND THE
ENTIRE DRISCOLL FARAH FAMILY. OUR HEARTS AND THOUGHTS ARE
WITH YOU DURING THIS DIFFICULT TIME.
MR. PRESIDENT, IF I MAY REQUEST THAT THIS IN MEMORIAM BE MADE
ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD THE REST I SUBMIT ON SUPERVISOR
MEL GARS MOTION. WE WILL HAVE THAT IN MEMORIAM
BE BY FROM THE FULL BOARD. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR MITCHELL.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER. THANK YOU.
COLLEAGUES, TODAY I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM TO SHARE FOR
JEANETTE ETHERIDGE, THE LONGTIME OWNER OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S TOSCA CAFE WHO RECENTLY PASSED AWAY AT THE AGE
OF 85. FOR MORE THAN THREE DECADES ON
COLUMBUS AVENUE, JEANETTE ETHERIDGE SERVED AS THE
PROPRIETOR OF TOSCA CAFE. SHE OWNED THE BAR BUT EVEN MORE
SHE OWNED THE ROOM. SEAN PENN ONCE A REGULAR
DESCRIBE JANETTE AS THE MOTHER AND MAYOR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
NIGHT. SHE WAS BORN IN CHINA.
A SOMEWHAT SURPRISING FACT SHAPED BY HER FAMILY'S JOURNEY.
HER PARENTS WERE THE CHILDREN OF ARMENIAN REFUGEES WHO FLED
THE GENOCIDE FIRST TO RUSSIA AND THEN TO CHINA.
SHE SPOKE RUSSIAN, CHINESE AND JAPANESE BEFORE SHE EVER
LEARNED ENGLISH. AS SHE MADE HER WAY TO SAN
FRANCISCO. SHE ATTENDED THE SAN FRANCISCO
ART INSTITUTE AND FOCUSED ON SCULPTURE.
>> SHE FOUND THE PRACTICE, HOWEVER, TO BE TOO SOLITARY
AND IN HER WORDS TOO DIFFICULT. >> FATE WOULD HAVE ANOTHER PLAN
FOR HER WHEN SHE WAS CHATTING WITH THE THEN OWNER OF TOSCA
CAFE WHO INFORMED HER THAT HE WAS GOING TO SHUT DOWN THE BAR
AND MOVE ON. SHE TOLD HER MOTHER THIS WHO
THEN PLEADED WITH HER TO BUY THE BAR.
THE RATIONALE. >> IT WAS THE FIRST BAR HER
MOTHER EVER VISITED IN THE UNITED STATES AND HER MOTHER
ALSO HAPPENED TO FAVOR TOSCA HOUSE CAPPUCCINO THE CHOCOLATE
A CONCOCTION THAT ACTUALLY CONTAINS NO COFFEE.
SO JEANNETTE SOON TOOK OVER THE KEYS AND IT WAS OFF TO THE
RACES. THROUGH THE YEARS, TOSCA
REGULARLY WELCOMED CELEBRITIES OF ALL STRIPES JAY-Z, FRANCIS
FORD COPPOLA, LEBRON JAMES, BILL MURRAY, HUNTER THOMPSON.
BUT MANAGED TO ALSO MAKE SURE THAT NEIGHBORHOOD REGULARS WERE
WELCOME. THAT SUMMED UP JEANNETTE WHO
JOHN MOSCONI DESCRIBED AS SIMULTANEOUSLY QUOTE BOTH FANCY
AND DOWN TO EARTH. TOSCA WAS A LIVING ROOM WHERE
BALLET DANCERS AND BUSINESSMEN, COPS AND POETS, LONGSHOREMEN
AND MOVIE STARS ALL ANSWERED TO JEANNETTE AND HER PARTNER
AND PROVIDING ENTERTAINMENT WAS A MASSIVE JUKEBOX FILLED WITH
HUNDREDS OF SONGS THAT SHE EACH HANDPICKED.
>> EACH SELECTION WAS SCRAWLED IN WRITING THAT SHE TOOK PRIDE
IN BEING THE ONLY ONE ABLE TO ACTUALLY READ.
SHE FAVORED OPERA MELODIES AND DEAN MARTIN.
THANKFULLY, JEANNETTE INCLUDED IN THOSE HUNDREDS OF SONGS ALSO
LAY MIO ON THE JUKEBOX, WHICH IS A FAMOUS NEAPOLITAN LOVE
SONG. AND THAT'S IMPORTANT BECAUSE
THAT'S THE NUMBER THAT BONO SPECIFICALLY REQUESTED WHEN HE
SHOWED UP AT TOSCA CAFE. ONE NIGHT WHILE AFTER CLOSING
TIME. HE THEN PROCEEDED TO JUMP ON
THE BAR BELT OUT THE BALLOT AND EVER SINCE HE WOULD SAY
THAT TOSCA CAFE WAS HIS FAVORITE HAUNT IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> JANETTE WAS GENEROUS OUTSIDE
THE BAR TOO. SHE WAS A FOUNDING BOARD MEMBER
OF NORTH BEACH CITIZENS AND SHAPED THEIR EARLY WORK
IN ADDRESSING HOMELESSNESS PARTICULARLY IN THE NORTH BEACH
NEIGHBORHOOD. SHE ALSO SERVED ON THE BOARD OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO INTERNATIONAL FILM FESTIVAL.
>> JANETTE WAS PROPOSED TO IN THE BOOTH AT TOSCA AND THE
COUPLE LATER DECIDED TO DIVORCE AT A BOOTH IN TOSCA.
YEARS LATER I'M TOLD IT WAS A DIFFERENT BOOTH THOUGH.
SHE ONCE SAID OF TOSCA IT'S LIKE A NEIGHBORHOOD BAR EXCEPT
THE ENTIRE CITY IS THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> JANETTE MADE A SINGLE ROOM IN NORTH BEACH FEEL LIKE THE
CENTER OF THE WORLD AND SHE MADE SURE THAT EVERYONE WHO
WALKED INTO IT BELIEVED THAT THEY BELONG THERE.
>> THAT WAS HER POWER. >> REST IN PEACE.
LEGEND OF TOSCA CAFE MOTHER AND MAYOR OF THE NIGHT.
JANETTE ETHERIDGE. MAY THERE BE A HOUSE CAPPUCCINO
AND A RED LEATHER BOOTH WAITING FOR YOU AND THE RESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SAUDER SUPERVISOR
CHERYL COLLEAGUES. I'D LIKE TO ADJOURN TODAY'S
MEETING IN MEMORY OF NAGAR GOWRI DAVY KOKA, A CHERISHED
MEMBER OF OUR DISTRICT TWO COMMUNITY WHOSE LIFE WAS
DEFINED BY RESILIENCE, KINDNESS, COURAGE AND ABOVE ALL
ON WAVERING LOVE. KNOWN TO ALL AS GOWRI SHE MADE
HER HOME AT THE MARTIN LUTHER TOWER IN CATHEDRAL HILL WHERE
SHE BECAME A PILLAR OF BOTH THAT COMMUNITY AND THE FAMILY
OF ST MARK'S CHURCH AND SHE SIMPLY LOVED SAN FRANCISCO FOR
HOW ACCEPTING AND DIVERSE IT ALLOWED HER TO BE.
GARY PASSED AWAY ON MAY 29TH, 2026.
>> SHE WAS BORN ON JUNE FIRST, 1954 IN A BLUE ROOM ANDHRA
PRADESH, INDIA AND EMIGRATED TO THE UNITED STATES IN 2000 SEVEN
MAKING SAN FRANCISCO HER HOME. ON MARCH 26TH, 2025, JUST OVER
A YEAR BEFORE HER PASSING, GARY FINALLY BECAME A NATURALIZED
UNITED STATES CITIZEN A BEACON OF ACCEPTANCE AND GRACE.
GARY, WELCOME PEOPLE FROM ALL WALKS OF LIFE BY MAKING
EVERYONE SHE MET FEEL SEEN, VALUED AND LOVED.
FOR MORE THAN 20 YEARS SHE SERVED AS A PRESCHOOL TEACHER
AND EDUCATOR SHAPING YOUNG LIVES WITH PATIENCE, WISDOM
AND WARMTH. A DEDICATED FAITH LEADER
AND ACTIVE MEMBER OF HER HINDU COMMUNITY, SHE WAS ALSO A
TRUSTED COUNSELOR AND SAFE HAVEN FOR IMMIGRANT WOMEN
NAVIGATING LIFE IN A NEW COUNTRY.
AS A PARENT ADVOCATE, GARY ENCOURAGED FAMILIES TO EMBRACE
AND SUPPORT THEIR AND TRANS CHILDREN.
SERVING AS A MOTHER TO MANY IN THE TRANS KIN R HIJRA
AND LGBTQ COMMUNITIES AND A SISTER TO COUNTLESS WOMEN, SHE
CHAMPIONED AUTISM AWARENESS AND HELPED BUILD SUPPORT
SYSTEMS FOR FAMILIES RAISING AUTISTIC CHILDREN ENSURING NO
ONE HAD TO FACE THOSE CHALLENGES ALONE.
>> A FOUNDATIONAL PILLAR DURING THE FORMATIVE YEARS OF PART OF
OUR BAY AREA, SHE HELPED BRING FAMILIES TOGETHER BRIDGING
PARENTS AND CHILDREN, SIBLINGS AND LOVED ONES THROUGH
UNDERSTANDING, ACCEPTANCE AND LOVE.
SHE ALSO HELPED OVERSEE GLOBAL COVID 19 RELIEF EFFORTS
AND TRANSGENDER LIVELIHOOD INITIATIVES.
>> GOWRI IS SURVIVED BY HER HUSBAND APPA RAO COCA AND HER
CHILDREN KAREN KOKA, SHRI KALA ROHAN KHUSHI LAXMAN AND ANJALI
RUMI. FROM THE VILLAGES OF INDIA TO
THE HEART OF SAN FRANCISCO GARY COCO'S JOURNEY WAS ONE OF
COURAGE AND CONVICTION AND IN LIVING IT FULLY SHE GAVE SO
MANY OTHERS THE STRENGTH TO LIVE AS THEIR TRUEST SELVES.
ANGEL IN HER FAMILY WOULD LOVE TO INVITE THE COMMUNITY FOR
GARY'S CELEBRATION OF LIFE ON TUESDAY JUNE 30TH FROM 6 P.M.
TO 8:15 P.M. AT ST MARK'S LUTHERAN CHURCH LOCATED AT 1111
O'FARRELL STREET. AND ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO THE
ENTIRE COCO FAMILY AND ALL WHO MOURN HER PASSING.
MAY HER MEMORY CONTINUE TO INSPIRE ACCEPTANCE, BELONGING
AND LOVE FOR ALL WHO CALL SAN FRANCISCO HOME.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SHERYL SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WONG. TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION SUPPORTING THE VETERANS OF FOREIGN WARS
IN OPPOSING DISABILITY BENEFIT CUTS CONTAINED IN THE PROPOSED
TAKE CARE OF AMERICA'S VETERANS ACT LEGISLATION THAT VETERANS
ADVOCATES HAVE CHARACTERIZED AS A BAIT AND SWITCH EFFORT TO
FUND NEW BENEFITS BY CUTTING EARNED DISABILITY COMPENSATION
AND SHIFTING CARE AWAY FROM THE VA AS A SOLDIER IN THE NATIONAL
GUARD. I HAVE A DEEP RESPECT FOR THE
WOMEN MEN AND WOMEN WHO SERVE AND FOR THE VETERANS WHO LIVE
OF INJURIES, ILLNESSES AND CONDITIONS CONNECTED TO
THAT SERVICE. WHEN SOMEONE TAKES THE OATH TO
SERVE OUR COUNTRY WE MAKE A COMMITMENT TO THEM AS WELL.
>> THAT COMMITMENT CANNOT END WHEN THEIR SERVICE ENDS
ESPECIALLY WHEN THEY COME HOME WITH SERVICE CONNECTED
DISABILITIES, DISABILITY COMPENSATION IS NOT A HANDOUT
IT IS A EARNED BENEFIT. >> IT IS PART OF THE PROMISE
THIS COUNTRY MAKES TO VETERANS WHO HAVE BORNE THE COST OF
SERVICE. >> THIS RESOLUTION FOCUSES ON
PROVISIONS IN HOUSE BILL 9237 AND SENATE BILL 474 FOR THE
PROPOSED TAKE CARE OF AMERICA'S VETERANS ACT THAT WOULD CHANGE
HOW THE VA RATES SERVICE CONNECTED TO AIDS AND SLEEP
APNEA. THESE CONDITIONS MAY BE COMMON
BUT THEY ARE NOT MINOR. FOR MANY VETERANS THEY AFFECT
SLEEP CONCENTRATION, MENTAL HEALTH WORK AND DAILY LIFE.
THE PROPOSED CHANGES COULD REDUCE OR ELIMINATE
COMPENSATION FOR MANY FUTURE CLAIMS NEWLY FILED CLAIMS,
REASSESSMENTS OR REEVALUATION EVEN OF SOME EXISTING RATINGS
ARE GRANDFATHERED. WE SHOULD BE CLEAR CUTTING
BENEFITS FOR FUTURE VETERANS IS STILL A CUT.
REDUCING COMPENSATION AVAILABLE TO VETERANS WHO FILE LATER IS
STILL CUT AND FUNDING ONE SET OF VETERANS BENEFITS BY
REDUCING EARNED BENEFITS FOR OTHER DISABLED VETERANS IS THE
WRONG APPROACH. THIS RESOLUTION ALSO URGES
CONGRESS TO PROTECT THE VA WORKFORCE AND PRESERVE ACCESS
TO DIRECT VA CARE. VETERANS DESERVE A STRONG,
ACCOUNTABLE V.A. SYSTEM STAFFED BY PROFESSIONAL AIDES WHO
UNDERSTAND THEIR NEEDS. AT ITS CORE, THIS RESOLUTION
SAYS THAT CONGRESS SHOULD ADVANCE VETERANS BENEFITS ON
THEIR OWN MERITS NOT BY BALANCING THE BOOKS ON THE
BACKS OF DISABLED VETERANS. I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR HIS
SUPPORT. I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A HEARING
REQUEST ON STAFFING LEVELS AT TERRYVILLE STATION WHICH SERVES
THE SUNSET PARK SITE AND SURROUNDING WEST SIDE
NEIGHBORHOODS. TURBEVILLE IS RESPONSIBLE FOR
THE LARGEST POLICE DISTRICT IN SAN FRANCISCO BY GEOGRAPHY
SERVING A LARGE RESIDENTIAL AREA FROM GOLDEN GATE PARK TO
THE COUNTY LINE AND FROM OCEAN BEACH TOWARD THE CENTER OF THE
CITY. WHEN STAFFING IS STRETCHED THIN
IN A DISTRICT THAT LARGE, IT AFFECTS MORE THAN JUST NUMBERS
ON THE CHART AND AFFECTS THE RESPONSE TIMES.
IT AFFECTS NEIGHBORHOOD PATROLS.
IT AFFECTS WHETHER OFFICERS CAN BE PRESENT ON COMMERCIAL
CORRIDORS, RESPOND TO PROPERTY CRIME, FOLLOW UP ON
INVESTIGATIONS AND PROVIDE VISIBLE ENFORCEMENT IN THE
NEIGHBORHOODS THEY SERVE. THIS HEARING WILL ASK THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT AND THE DEPARTMENT HUMAN RESOURCES TO
REPORT ON CURRENT SWORN AND CIVILIAN STAFFING
VACANCIES, RECRUITMENT, HIRING AND RETENTION AND WHAT IS
NEEDED TO BETTER SUPPORT TERRYVILLE STATION AND THE WEST
SIDE COMMUNITIES IT SERVES. >> IN ADDITION, I'M INTRODUCING
A SECOND HEARING ON THE CITY'S STREET TREE MAINTENANCE PROGRAM
INCLUDING HOW OFTEN TREES ARE PRUNED.
HOW THAT WORK IS SCHEDULED AND HOW THE CITY MANAGES THE
SIDEWALK AND INFRASTRUCTURE DAMAGE CAUSED BY TREE ROOTS.
AS DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR ROOT MANAGEMENT AND TREE
PRUNING ARE ONE MOST COMMON ISSUES THAT I HEAR FROM MY
CONSTITUENTS. STREET TREES ARE AN IMPORTANT
PART OF OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. THEY PROVIDE SHADE, IMPROVE AIR
QUALITY, HELP WITH STORMWATER AND MAKE OUR STREETS MORE
LIVABLE. BUT THEY ALSO REQUIRE REGULAR
MAINTENANCE WHEN PRUNING IS DELAYED, TREES CAN BECOME
OVERGROWN BLOCK SIGNS OR STREET LIGHTS INTERFERE WITH OVERHEAD
WHITE LINES AND CREATE SAFETY CONCERNS WHEN TREE ROOTS DAMAGE
SIDEWALKS, CURBS SEWERS OR OTHER PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE.
RESIDENTS NEED A CLEAR AND TIMELY PROCESS FOR REPAIR.
THIS HEARING WILL GIVE PUBLIC WORKS THE BUREAU OF URBAN
FORESTRY AND THE URBAN FORESTRY COUNCIL AN OPPORTUNITY TO
EXPLAIN THE CURRENT MAINTENANCE SCHEDULE HOW PRIORITIES ARE
DETERMINED, WHAT RESOURCES ARE AVAILABLE AND WHERE THE TREE
MAY NEED OR THE CITY MAY NEED TO IMPROVE COORDINATION
AND RESPONSIVENESS. I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT. THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> I'D LIKE TO BE ADDED TO
SUPERVISOR CHERYL'S IN MEMORIAM IF HE HAS NO OBJECTIONS TO
THAT. >> NO OBJECTION.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
AND WITH THAT, LET'S GO TO OUR 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER.
>> YES, THE 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER IS THE RECOGNITION OF
COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY
OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> AND I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE
CATHERINE MOORE TO COME FORWARD .
YOU COME UP, YOU GO TO THE MICROPHONE AND I SAY NICE
THINGS ABOUT YOU AND THEN SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES ARE ALSO GOING
TO SAY NICE THINGS ABOUT YOU. ALL RIGHT.
WE ARE HONORING CATHERINE MOORE AS SHE APPROACHES THE END OF
WHAT HAS BEEN 20 YEARS OF SERVICE AS A MEMBER OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PLANNING COMMISSION. CATHERINE IS AN ACCOMPLISHED
ARCHITECT AND URBAN DESIGNER WHO PRIOR TO HER TIME ON THE
PLANNING COMMISSION LED SKIDMORE, OWINGS AND OWENS
AND MERRILL'S URBAN DESIGN STUDIO IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR 27
YEARS. AFTER STUDYING ARCHITECTURE
IN EUROPE AND EARNING A MASTER'S DEGREE FROM THE YALE
SCHOOL OF ARCHITECTURE, CATHERINE WENT ON TO WORK ON
AND LEAD URBAN DESIGN AND PLANNING PROJECTS IN THE
UNITED STATES. EUROPE, ASIA AND THE MIDDLE
EAST INCLUDING THE DESIGN OF A NEW CITY'S MIXED USE
DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS WATERFRONT DEVELOPMENT, TRANSPORTATION
AND MORE. MANY OF THESE PROJECTS HAVE WON
A AWARDS. KATHRYN HAS ALSO WRITTEN
AND LECTURED EXTENSIVELY ON URBAN DESIGN AND PLANNING
ISSUES BOTH NATIONALLY AND INTERNATIONALLY AND TAUGHT
FOR TEN YEARS AS A VISITING PROFESSOR AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
STUTTGART IN GERMANY. HER SERVICE TO THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO BEGAN IN 2001 WHEN SHE WAS
APPOINTED TO THE TREASURE ISLAND CITIZEN'S ADVISORY BOARD
BY SUPERVISOR MARK LENO. SHE SERVED IN THAT ROLE UNTIL
2015 HELPING GUIDE THE WORK THE THAT WOULD EVENTUALLY LEAD TO
THE APPROVAL OF THE TREASURE ISLAND MASTER PLAN IN 2005.
THEN MAYOR NEWSOM APPOINTED HER TO THE PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
WATERFRONT DESIGN ADVISORY COMMITTEE WHERE SHE HAS HELPED
SHAPE SEVERAL OF THE PROJECTS ON THE CITY'S WATERFRONT
INCLUDING THE EXPLORATORIUM, THE GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS ARENA
AND PIER 70. SINCE HER APPOINTMENT TO THE
PLANNING COMMISSION IN 2006, KATHRYN HAS SERVED UNDER FOUR
MAYORS AND HAS WORKED ALONGSIDE FOUR PLANNING DIRECTORS, 45
SUPERVISORS, 24 PLANNING COMMISSIONERS, THREE ZONING
ADMINISTRATORS AND TWO COMMISSION SECRETARIES.
HER METICULOUSLY REVIEW OF PROJECTS RIGOROUS ANALYSIS
AND COMMITMENT TO DESIGN EXCELLENCE HAS QUITE LITERALLY
HELPED SHAPE THE LANDSCAPE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
SHE'S WORKED ON THE MARKET. OCTAVIA PLAN THE EASTERN
NEIGHBORHOODS PLAN TRANSIT CENTER DISTRICT PLAN AMERICA'S
CUP 34, THE GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS ARENA AT MISSION BAY
MARKET STREET HUB MISSION 2020 ACTION PLAN AND MULTIPLE
ITERATIONS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO HOUSING ELEMENT.
SHE'S SHAPED THE CITY'S RESPONSE TO CITYWIDE CHALLENGES
AS WELL INCLUDING THE EXPANSION OF TRANSIT ORIENTED PROJECTS,
PRESERVATION OF OPEN SPACES AND IMPLEMENTATION OF
SUSTAINABLE BUILDING PRACTICES TO COMBAT CLIMATE CHANGE.
KATHRYN CONSISTENTLY ADVOCATED FOR THOUGHTFUL, SUSTAINABLE
GROWTH BALANCING THE NEED FOR NEW DEVELOPMENT WITH RESPECT
AND CARE FOR SAN FRANCISCO'S UNIQUE HISTORY, CULTURE
AND CHARACTER. SHE'S EARNED RECOGNITION FROM
NEIGHBORHOOD ORGANIZATIONS ACROSS THE CITY FOR HER FOCUS
ON AFFORDABILITY, LOCAL VOICES AND NEIGHBORHOOD INTERESTS.
NO ONE ON THE COMMISSION COMMISSION HAS WORKED HARDER
SPENDING COUNTLESS HOURS MASTERING COMPLEX PLANNING
CODES ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORTS AND DEVELOPMENT
PROPOSALS. BEYOND HER TECHNICAL EXPERTISE
AND INCREDIBLE WORK ETHIC, THOSE WHO'VE WORKED WITH
KATHRYN HAVE PRAISED HER INDEPENDENCE AND INTEGRITY.
WOE BE TO ANY BOARD PRESIDENT WHO WOULD TRY TO INFLUENCE HER
OR HER THINKING ON ANY MATTER DURING HER TENURE ON THE
PLANNING COMMISSION. SHE WAS UNANIMOUSLY ELECTED TO
SERVE AS COMMISSION VICE PRESIDENT SEVEN TIMES.
KATHRYN MY COLLEAGUES GOING TO BE ABLE TO SPEAK FOR THEMSELVES
BUT ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WE ARE INCREDIBLY
GRATEFUL FOR YOUR TIME, YOUR CONTRIBUTIONS AND WE WISH YOU
THE VERY, VERY BEST IN THE YEARS AHEAD.
AND I WILL START WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENEM AND COMMISSIONER, I JUST WANT
TO SAY THROUGHOUT YOUR YEARS OF SERVICE YOU HAVE BROUGHT
THOUGHTFUL LEADERSHIP, INTEGRITY AND A DEEP COMMITMENT
TO THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO. YOU HAVE CONSISTENTLY BEEN A
CHAMPION FOR COMMUNITY VOICES AND RESIDENTS AND SHARING THEIR
CONCERNS, NEEDS AND ASPIRATIONS OF NEIGHBORHOODS REMAINED AT
THE CENTER OF IMPORTANT PLANNING DECISIONS.
YOUR UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO LISTENING TO AND ADVOCATING FOR
THE PEOPLE MOST IMPACTED BY DEVELOPMENT HAS EARNED YOU SO
MUCH TRUST AND RESPECT OF COMMUNITIES ACROSS THIS CITY.
THROUGHOUT YOUR TENURE YOU WERE NEVER AFRAID TO TAKE ON
DIFFICULT ISSUES OR ENGAGE IN TOUGH BATTLES WHEN THE
INTERESTS OF RESIDENTS AND NEIGHBORHOODS WERE AT STAKE
. YOU APPROACHED EVERY CHALLENGE
WITH COURAGE, CONVICTION AND A STRONG SENSE OF PURPOSE EVEN
IN THE FACE OF SIGNIFICANT OPPOSITION.
YOU REMAIN STEADFAST IN YOUR PRINCIPLES AND NEVER WAVERED
FROM YOUR COMMITMENT TO WHAT YOU BELIEVED TO BE BEST FOR SAN
FRANCISCO. YOUR WILLINGNESS TO STAND FIRM,
ASK HARD QUESTIONS AND ADVOCATE FOR THOUGHTFUL AND COMMUNITY
CENTERED OUTCOMES DISTINGUISH YOU AS A RESPECTED AND TRUSTED
LEADER. YOUR DEDICATION TO RESPONSIBLE
PLANNING EQUITABLE DEVELOPMENT ,HISTORIC PRESERVATION
AND MEANINGFUL PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT HAS HELPED SHAPE A
STRONGER AND MORE INCLUSIVE SAN FRANCISCO.
YOUR ABILITY TO BALANCE THE NEEDS OF NEIGHBORHOODS,
RESIDENTS, BUSINESSES AND FUTURE GENERATIONS HAS MADE
YOU CONTINUOUSLY A RESPECTED LEADER AND POWERFUL ADVOCATE
FOR COMMUNITY CENTERED PLANNING.
>> AS YOU CONCLUDE YOUR SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO, WE ARE LOSING AN EXTRAORDINARY, EXTRAORDINARY
AMOUNT OF INSTITUTIONAL KNOWLEDGE, EXPERIENCE
AND HISTORICAL PERSPECTIVE. YOUR DEEP UNDERSTANDING OF SAN
FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOODS PLANNING, HISTORY AND CIVIC
PROCESSES HAS BEEN INVALUABLE IN HELPING GUIDE THOUGHTFUL
DECISION MAKING DURING TIMES OF BOTH OPPORTUNITY AND CHALLENGE.
YOUR WISDOM STEADY LEADERSHIP AND COMMITMENT TO THE PUBLIC
GOOD WILL BE GREATLY MISSED. THE DISTRICT TEN OFFICE WILL
ESPECIALLY FEEL YOUR ABSENCE. OVER THE YEARS OUR OFFICE HAS
HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF WORKING CLOSELY WITH YOU COMMISSIONER
MOORE ON SOME OF THE MOST COMPLEX AND CONSEQUENTIAL
ISSUES FACING OUR COMMUNITIES. MY CHIEF OF STAFF PERCY BURCH
WILL LIKELY MISS YOU THE MOST. HE SPENT COUNTLESS HOURS
WORKING TOGETHER CHALLENGING PROJECTS, ADDRESSING COMMUNITY
CONCERNS AND FINDING SOLUTIONS TO DIFFICULT PROJECT PROBLEMS.
>> THOSE CONVERSATIONS WERE ROOTED IN A SHARED COMMITMENT
TO RESIDENTS AND A BELIEF THAT GOVERNMENT WORKS BEST WHEN
PEOPLE ARE WILLING TO LISTEN AND COLLABORATE AND STAY
FOCUSED ON THE COMMUNITY. COMMISSIONER MOORE YOU WERE
ALWAYS GENEROUS WITH YOUR TIME, THOUGHTFUL IN YOUR APPROACH
AND AND WAVERING IN YOUR DEDICATION TO GETTING THINGS
RIGHT. I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR
YOUR YEARS OF SERVICE LEADERSHIP AND STEADFAST
COMMITMENT TO THE RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO.
YOUR LEGACY WILL BE DEFINED NOT ONLY BY THE PROJECTS YOU HELPED
SHAPE BUT BY THE COUNTLESS COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHOSE VOICES
YOU WORK TIRELESSLY TO ELEVATE AND PROTECT.
SAN FRANCISCO IS A BETTER CITY BECAUSE OF YOUR SERVICE AND I
WISH YOU CONTINUED SUCCESS IN THE YEARS AHEAD.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT
AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON .
THAT WAS REALLY WELL SAID. I AM ONE OF THE PEOPLE WHO HAD
THE HONOR AND PLEASURE OF WORKING ALONGSIDE COMMISSIONER
MOORE FOR MANY YEARS ON THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
IN ADDITION TO THANKING YOU AS OTHER SUPERVISORS HAVE FOR YOUR
GREAT SERVICE TO SAN FRANCISCO ,I WANT TO THANK YOU
PERSONALLY BECAUSE YOU TAUGHT ME A LOT.
YOU HAVE A CLEAR AND CONSISTENT VOICE ABOUT EVERYTHING TO DO
WITH URBAN DESIGN AND THE ESTHETICS OF THE ARCHITECTURE
OF SAN FRANCISCO. BUT IT'S NOT JUST THE TECHNICAL
KNOWLEDGE. IT WAS THE PASSION AND LOVE
THAT YOU BRING TO IT AND ALWAYS FINDING NEW THINGS TO BE ABLE
TO ZERO IN ON FOCUS AND CLEARLY ARTICULATE AND THEN CONVEY TO
OTHERS SO THAT WE COULD UNDERSTAND THAT POINT OF VIEW
AND DO IT CONVINCINGLY. TECHNICALLY PROFICIENT ONLY AT
CLEAR ON WHAT THE CODE SAYS BUT ALSO WITH THE DEEP KNOWLEDGE OF
THE PEOPLE AND THE COMMUNITIES THAT WE ALL SERVE.
SO I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING THAT YOU'VE GIVEN US
BUT ALSO FOR YOUR WARMTH AS A COLLEAGUE, FOR YOUR HEART, YOUR
PASSION AND THE CARE WITH WHICH YOU ALWAYS ENGAGED
IN CONVERSATIONS WITH COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND THE PUBLIC AND EVEN
THE STAFF. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
EVERYTHING THAT YOU HAVE DONE FOR ALL OF US AND WE WILL MISS
YOU DEARLY. I KNOW THAT YOU'LL STILL BE
AROUND DOING STUFF IN THE ARCHITECTURE COMMUNITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO BUT WE WILL MISS YOU ON THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
YOU BRING A WEALTH OF EXPERIENCE NOT JUST ABOUT
ARCHITECTURE OR DESIGN AND URBAN PLANNING BUT ABOUT
PEOPLE ABOUT THE RELATIONSHIPS THAT WE HAVE BETWEEN ONE
ANOTHER, ABOUT THE COMMUNITIES AND YOU KNOW THAT THE PEOPLE
AND FAMILIES THAT WE ALL SERVE. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH,
COMMISSIONER MOORE, VICE PRESIDENT MOORE FOR EVERYTHING
YOU HAVE DONE. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU
FOR CRISIS MANAGEMENT. >> COMMISSIONER MOORE YOUR
LEGACIES ARE HIGH. COMMISSIONER MOORE.
>> YEAH HI. HERE.
>> YOUR LEGACY ON THE PLANNING COMMISSION IT'S FOREIGN
DIRECTLY INTO THE FABRIC OF OUR CITY.
I REALLY APPRECIATE THAT YOU LOOKED AT EVERY PROJECT THROUGH
A LONG TERM LENS ALWAYS ASKING HOW ARE BUILDING WHAT IMPACT
THE EVERYDAY LIVES OF THE PEOPLE LIVING AROUND IT NOW
AND IN THE FUTURE. >> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
YOUR MANY YEARS OF SERVICES AND LEADERSHIP.
AND I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO ADD MYSELF AS A CO-SPONSOR FOR THIS
RESOLUTION. >> THANK YOU.
CONGRATS FOR YOUR RETIREMENT. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR
HONORING COMMISSIONER MOORE. COMMISSIONER MOORE.
IT IS A PRIVILEGE AND AN HONOR TO BE SERVING AS A SUPERVISOR
WHILE YOU ARE PLANNING COMMISSIONER TOGETHER.
THERE WERE A LOT OF CONVERSATION.
WHAT IT'S AMAZING ABOUT YOU IS THAT YOU NOT ONLY UNDERSTAND
THE TECHNICAL LAND USE POLICY YOU'RE ABLE TO TRANSLATE IT FOR
ME, ALI AND MANY OF US IN A WAY HOW ACTUALLY IMPACT PEOPLE
AND HOW THE CHANGE OF LAND USE WHILE OFTENTIMES BEEN TECHNICAL
THE REALITY HOW IT RESULTS IN IMPACTING LIVES OF MANY.
>> YOU HAVE DONE TREMENDOUS WORK FOR SAN FRANCISCANS IN THE
BEST INTEREST OF SAN FRANCISCANS AND FOR THAT WE'RE
SO GRATEFUL TO YOU. >> WE ALSO KNOW IT HAS NOT BEEN
EASY. IT HAS NOT BEEN EASY TO BE SORT
OF THIS VOICE OF REASON AND THE VOICE OF TRYING TO ARTICULATE
THROUGH LAND USE POLICY BUT ALSO TECHNICAL CHANGES AND WHAT
THAT ACTUALLY MEANS NOT JUST FOR THE MOMENT BUT FOR DECADES
TO COME FOR THE FUTURE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I DO BELIEVE THAT WE'RE IN A CRITICAL POINT AND THE CRITICAL
TIME AND I'M JUST WANT TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE NOT ONLY
FOR YOUR DECADES OF PAST OF YOUR SERVICE BUT I HAD A
CONFIDENCE THAT I THINK THERE ARE I THINK MANY ARE GOING TO
SEE A DIFFERENT YOU AS YOU NO LONGER SERVE AS OUR PLANNING
COMMISSIONER AND THAT YOU ACTUALLY ABLE TO BE OUTSIDE
AND AS A AS A COMMUNITY ADVOCATE IT WILL BE VERY
DIFFERENT AND I SAY CITY HALL BETTER WATCH OUT.
>> THANK YOU. >> VICE PRESIDENT IF I MAY 1ST
MORE TWO. I JUST WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE
COMMISSIONER GILBERT WILLIAMS IS HERE AND I THINK MAYBE
TERESA IMPERIO MAYBE IS SOMEWHERE TOO.
>> BUT I JUST ALSO WANT TO THANK THEM FOR THEIR SERVICE.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN VICE PRESIDENT
MOORE THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> OKAY.
>> MANY OF THE THINGS I WANTED TO SAY TO YOU YOU PICKED UP ON
YOUR OWN. SOMEBODY GAVE YOU MY RÉSUMÉ.
I NORMALLY DON'T SPEAK ABOUT MYSELF TO SUCH A LEVEL OF
DETAIL, BUT THANK YOU. THANK YOU TO ALL OF YOU FOR
ACKNOWLEDGING ME. I KNOW.
I KNOW SOME OF YOU BETTER THAN OTHERS.
SOME OF THEM ARE NEW AND I HAVE NOT HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO
DIRECTLY WORK WITH YOU. >> HOWEVER, PRESIDENT MEN,
THANK YOU FOR THE HONOR AND THANK YOU FOR THE TRUST
THAT YOU AND YOUR COLLEAGUES PAST AND PRESENT HAVE EXTENDED
TO ME THROUGHOUT THESE 15 AS FAR AS THESE 20 YEARS.
YOU LOSE TRACK WHEN YOU DON'T COUNT TIME YOU JUST DO IT.
SO IT'S 20 YEARS, HUH? THANK YOU.
AVOID SECRETS. SORRY.
ANGELA CARRILLO. SECRETARY CARRILLO FOR INFO.
>> SOME OF YOU WHO DON'T KNOW ACTUALLY OFFICIATED AND SWORE
ME IN FOR MY FOURTH APPOINTMENT ON SEPTEMBER 18TH, 2018 AND HAS
ALWAYS BEEN AVAILABLE WITH WISDOM AND ADVICE.
>> THANK YOU. >> PLEASE LET ME ALLOW ME A FEW
MINUTES TO REMINISCE AND I WILL NOT GO INTO TOO MUCH DETAIL.
IT'S NOT MEMORY LANE BUT IT'S TOUCHING ON A COUPLE OF
IMPORTANT POINTS THAT ARE BENCHMARKS AND HAVE ALL COME
TOGETHER TO TALK TO YOU OF WHAT MAY TAKE AWAY IS FROM MY
SERVICE PEOPLE ARE ASKING ME WHAT COMES TO MIND WHEN YOU ARE
LOOKING BACK AT 20 YEARS OF SERVICE?
IS IT ENDLESS MEETINGS, HUGE COMMISSION PACKETS, LONG
HEARINGS, LATE NIGHT GET TOGETHERS WHEN THE GARAGE IS
ALREADY CLOSED? NO, THERE'S SOMETHING ELSE.
>> WHAT IS IT? IS IT STATS THAT COUNT A
SUPERVISOR A PRESIDENT MEN WOMEN TOUCHED ON A FEW NUMBERS.
>> THOSE ARE THINGS THAT FLOW THROUGH YOUR MIND LIKE 936
MEETINGS 5869 PROJECT APPROVALS INDEED FOUR MAYORS INDEED 45
SUPERVISORS INCLUDING THOSE WHO SIT HERE AND FOR 26 FELLOW
COMMISSIONERS WITH WHOM YOU LEARN TO WORK EVERY FOUR YEARS
AND IN CYCLES FOR PLANNING DIRECTORS ALL OF DIFFERENT AGE
AND BACKGROUND THREE ZONING ADMINISTRATOR LEADERS TWO
COMMISSION SECRETARIES. THOUSANDS AND THOUSANDS OF
PEOPLE MANY OF WHOSE NAMES YOU REMEMBER AFTER YOU SEE THEM YOU
IN YOU'RE ON YOUR COUCH BEING IN FRONT OF THE PLANNING
COMMISSION. >> WHAT WHAT IS IT?
WHAT IS IT? WHAT STICKS?
AND I GOT TO REFER TO SOME OF MY NOTES BECAUSE THERE'S A LOT
THAT HAS STUCK. WHAT HAS REALLY SHAPED ME IS
INDEED THE VOICES OF OUR CITIZENS AND THAT GROWS ON YOU
SLOWLY. IT DOES TODAY IT IS A DIVERSE
AND PASSIONATE VOICE OF SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOODS THAT
HAVE HAD SOME MOST PROFOUND IMPACT ON ME.
THESE ARE THE VOICES OF WHAT I REFER TO AS TWO URBAN DWELLERS
GENUINE NEIGHBORS, PEOPLE WHO CARE ALL THIS HAS TOUCHED,
MOVED AND INSPIRED ME AND BECOME CLEARER AND MORE
INTO FOCUS AS YEARS WENT BY IN THE BEGINNING YOU MAKE A
NOTE BUT AS IT OCCURS AGAIN AND AGAIN IT GROWS ON YOU AS IF
YOU'RE DEVELOPING AN OLD DEAR FRIEND.
>> THESE VOICES ARE VOICES OF PEOPLE WHO DO NOT ONLY CARE
ABOUT THEMSELVES AND WHAT WORKS IN THEIR OWN NEIGHBORHOODS BUT
THESE ARE VOICES OF PEOPLE WHO UNDERSTAND THE CITY AS AN URBAN
CONTRACT AND WHAT MATTERS TO THE CITY AT LARGE.
>> OVER THE YEARS I'VE BECOME A BETTER LISTENER AND A BETTER
AND STRONGER, MORE INFORMED VOICE FOR NEIGHBORHOOD CONCERNS
WHICH CALLS FOR CONSTANT AWARENESS OF SOCIAL, RACIAL
AND ENVIRONMENTAL EQUITY ISSUES .
>> AND TO THAT END ONE OF MY OBJECTIVES HAVE ALWAYS BEEN
BROADENING AS SUPERVISOR MALAGA SAID THE DIALOG AMONG MY FELLOW
PLANNING COMMISSIONERS BRIDGING THE GAP BETWEEN THE TECHNICAL
ELEMENTS OF PLANNING AND THE EMOTIONAL COMPONENT THAT
INFLUENCES, INFLUENCES AND OFTEN SHAPES DECISION
MAKING. >> IT'S A VERY, VERY SUBTLE
POINT. WE CAN NOT ONLY DRAW ON OUR
MOTION WHAT IS WIDE WAS WRONG BUT FINGER AND THE WIND.
THERE IS INDEED A BALANCE IN HOW WE DO THINGS IN THIS
PARTICULAR CITY. >> IN THIS DIALOG, LISTENING TO
THE VOICE OF OUR NEIGHBORS IS A MOST POWERFUL TOOL FOR
ATTAINABLE SOLUTION. >> THIS IS WHAT I HAVE LEARNED
OVER THE LAST 20 YEARS. >> JUST AS I'M SURE THERE ARE
SOME OF YOU WHO WOULD SAY I'M LOSING MY TRAIN OF THOUGHT.
I'M SORRY I GOT TO STICK MOST MY COMMENTS HERE.
>> HERE WE GO. SORRY THERE MAY BE SOME OF YOU
WHO ARE CURIOUS ABOUT THE WAY WE WERE 20 YEARS AGO AND YOU ME
BEST YOU MAY BE SURPRISED. YOU'RE BURDENED WITH ISSUES
WHICH SEEM TO BE SO OVERWHELMINGLY NEW
AND UNSOLVABLE. BUT THROUGHOUT THE PAST 20
YEARS THE CITY'S PRESSING HOUSING SHORTAGE HAS ALWAYS
BEEN AT THE FOREFRONT OF PLANNING.
20 YEARS OF PRESSING HOUSING ISSUES THE SIGNIFICANT LACK OF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING, THE THREAT OF GENTRIFICATION, RISING
INCOME GAPS AND DISPLACEMENT OF VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES IT IS
JUST AS SERIOUS AS IT WAS 20 YEARS AGO.
>> IN CLOSING I AM HONORED TO HAVE SERVED AS A COMMISSIONER
FOR FIVE TERMS AND I THANK YOU FOR HAVING SUPPORTED ME
THROUGHOUT THIS TIME. >> AND I'M GOING TO SAY GOODBYE
FOR NOW. >> BUT I AM LOOKING FORWARD TO
PERHAPS IN A YEAR OR SO FROM NOW TO SAYING HELLO AGAIN
AND IMAGINE MYSELF IN FRONT OF THIS BOARD PERHAPS AS A
NEIGHBOR WHO DEEPLY CARES ABOUT SAN FRANCISCO IN ITS SEARCH FOR
GOOD PLANNING, FOR GOOD CITY PLANNING AND URBAN DESIGN.
>> THANK YOU TO ALL OF YOU. THANK YOU.
CATHERINE MOORE. WE ARE WE WE HAVE A COUPLE OF
YEARS. >> WE HAVE A COUPLE OF THINGS
FOR YOU TODAY, CATHERINE. >> LATER IN OUR AGENDA WE'RE
GOING TO BE VOTING ON A RESOLUTION COMMENDING YOU
AND THANKS TO OUR EXTRAORDINARY CLERK AND HER STAFF.
WE HAVE A FRAMED COPY OF THAT RESOLUTION FOR YOU.
>> AND THEN I HAVE THE TRADITIONAL CERTIFICATE OF
HONOR THAT WE GIVE OUT TO FOLKS FOR OUR SPECIAL ACCOMMODATIONS.
I'M AN INVITE YOU INTO THE WELL FOR A PHOTO WITH THE BOARD.
THANK YOU. BE PUBLIC.
YEAH, IT'S ME. ALL RIGHT.
THREE, TWO, ONE AND TWO
YEARS. WE'RE TALKING TO GET.
>> NEXT UP, WE HAVE FROM DISTRICT SEVEN SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. THANK YOU.
AND I'M GOING TO HAVE FOLKS MAYBE SIT AROUND UNTIL YOU'RE
READY TO TO COME UP AND SPEAK. BUT COLLEAGUES, TODAY I AM
HONORED TO JOIN SUPERVISE OWNERS WALTON AND FIELDER'S
OFFICE IN RECOGNIZING MARY SAID VOLUNTEERS AS SHE CELEBRATES
THEIR 100TH BIRTHDAY. >> SO LET'S GIVE IT UP FOR MARY
AND FOR THOSE 100 YEARS TO COMMEND HER FOR A LIFE MARKED
BY RESILIENCE, FAMILY DEVOTION AND HARD WORK.
MARY WAS BORN IN L.A. TO A LARGE MEXICAN AMERICAN FAMILY
WHERE SHE WAS ONE OF 13 CHILDREN.
>> HER PARENTS ORIGINALLY FROM PUNJAB AND SINALOA, IMMIGRATED
TO L.A. IN THE 1920S AND HER FATHER WORKED ON THE UNION
PACIFIC RAILROAD. MARY CAME OF AGE DURING THE
GREAT DEPRESSION A TIME WHEN HARDSHIP AND ECONOMIC
INSTABILITY FOR MANY LATINO FAMILIES WAS THE NORM.
>> HER STORY REFLECTS THE STRENGTH AND PERSEVERANCE OF
THESE FAMILIES AS THEY SUPPORTED EACH OTHER AND HELPED
BUILD CALIFORNIA INDIA. >> SHE GRADUATED FROM BISHOP
CANADY HIGH SCHOOL IN 1943 WHERE SHE STUDIED BUSINESS
ADMINISTRATION AND BOOKKEEPING .
>> AND THROUGH HARD WORK AND SKILL SHE BUILT A CAREER
IN ADVANCE OF POSITIONS TO POSITIONS OF RESPONSIBILITY
INCLUDING OFFICE MANAGEMENT. THROUGHOUT HER LIFE MARY
CONTRIBUTED TO HER FAMILY'S STABILITY WHILE WORKING RAISING
HER CHILDREN, MANAGING A HOUSEHOLD, SEWING AND KEEPING
BOOKS FOR MULTIPLE BUSINESSES. >> AFTER PASSING THAT THROUGH
THE PASSING OF HER HUSBAND LAURA CERVANTES, WHO WAS A
WORLD WAR TWO VETERAN, MARY MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO
AND BECAME PRESIDENT OF THE MISSION AND BERNAL HEIGHTS
IN DISTRICT NINE. >> TODAY MARY CONTINUES TO BE
AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF THE COMMUNITY BY CROCHETING
CHILDREN'S HATS TO HOLIDAY PROGRAMS SERVING FAMILIES
IN NEED. AND AS MARY CERVANTES
CELEBRATES THIS EXCEPTIONAL MILESTONE, WE HONOR HER LIFE
IN HER COMMITMENT TO RESILIENCE AND FAMILY DEVOTION.
WE WILL BE FORMALLY VOTING ON A RESOLUTION AS WELL COLLEAGUES
IN HER HONOR LATER TODAY IN THIS MEETING.
SO I WANT TO WISH YOU A AN INCREDIBLY HAPPY BIRTHDAY,
MARY. WE DO HAVE HER DAUGHTER
AND SERVANT THIS YEAR WHO'S GOING TO SAY A FEW WORDS ON HER
BEHALF. >> WELCOME AND HOPE.
>> AND HOLD UP THOUGH. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
SO MUCH, PRESIDENT. AND THANK YOU SO MUCH,
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> AND I JUST WANTED TO SAY I
KNOW SUPERVISOR MELGAR SAID IT ALL BUT YOU CAN TELL A LOT FROM
SOMEONE IN THEIR FRUITFUL LIFE FROM THEIR OFFSPRING AS WE WILL
BE HEARING FROM HER DAUGHTER. AND I JUST WANT TO SAY HAPPY
100TH BIRTHDAY. WE SHOULD ALL LIVE TO BE SO
YOUNG. >> HAPPY BIRTHDAY.
WELL, YOU KNOW ME AS AN SERVANT IS AND I'M NOT HERE AS A
BUSINESS SMALL BUSINESS ADVOCATE OR PROVIDING INSIGHT
INTO YOUR LEGISLATION. >> YOU'LL HEAR FROM ME LATER AT
A DIFFERENT EVENT. >> BUT I'M HERE TO SORT OF
CELEBRATE MY MOM AND JUST THE GIFTS THAT SHE'S GIVEN ME.
SORRY AND CARE ABOUT OTHERS AND HER SELF-DETERMINATION
WHICH A LOT OF YOU KNOW THAT I DO HAVE THAT SELF
DETERMINATION. I DON'T LET UP.
>> SO I WANT TO THANK YOU. SHE'S MADE IT THROUGH THE
DEPRESSION AS A LITTLE KID SIMILAR.
>> YES. SIMILAR TO WHAT THE IMMIGRANTS
ARE GOING THROUGH. THIS CITY IS LIVING IN FEAR BUT
SHE SURVIVED THAT AND I THANK YOU ALL FOR THIS RECOGNITION
AT THIS
D-10 SUPERVISOR WELCOME. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
PRESIDENT MADAM IN COLLEAGUES IT IS MY PRIVILEGE AND HONOR TO
RISE AND RECOGNIZE AN EXTRAORDINARY PUBLIC SERVANT
AND ADVOCATE PATTY LEE. >> PATTY PATTY IS RETIRING FROM
THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC DEFENDER'S OFFICE AFTER 49
YEARS OF SERVICE TO PUBLIC DEFENDER CLIENTS IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. PATTY WAS BORN AND RAISED
IN SAN FRANCISCO. SHE MOVED FROM CHINATOWN TO THE
RICHMOND DISTRICT AS A CHILD AT A TIME WHEN THERE WERE NO OTHER
CHINESE FAMILIES IN THAT COMMUNITY.
HER GRANDFATHER OPENED HIS STORE IN CHINATOWN AND HER
FATHER CAME OVER THROUGH ANGEL ISLAND AT AGE FOUR.
PATTY ATTENDED SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC SCHOOLS LAFAYETTE
ELEMENTARY, PRESIDIO MIDDLE SCHOOL WHERE SHE WAS THE
SCHOOL'S SECOND EVER GIRL PRESIDENT AND WASHINGTON HIGH
SCHOOL. SHE CHOSE TO BECOME A PUBLIC
DEFENDER BECAUSE SHE SAW THE SYSTEM WAS BROKEN AND SAW HOW
THAT BROKEN SYSTEM IMPACTED PEOPLE CLOSE TO HER.
PATTY STARTED AT THE DOWNTOWN OFFICE AT THE HALL OF JUSTICE.
FIVE YEARS LATER SHE WAS ASKED TO JOIN THE JUVENILE UNIT
AND THAT'S WHERE SHE FOUND HER LIFE'S WORK.
SHE BEGAN REPRESENTING YOUNG CLIENTS IN 1981 AND WENT ON TO
LEAD THE YOUTH DEFENDER UNIT FORMERLY THE JUVENILE UNIT.
AS MANAGING ATTORNEY FOR OVER 30 YEARS UNDER HER LEADERSHIP,
SAN FRANCISCO NEARLY ELIMINATED STATE INSTITUTIONAL COMMITMENT
FOR YOUTH. THROUGH HER WORK DEVELOPING
AND PROMOTING SOCIAL WORK SERVICES AND DEFENSE BASED
DISPOSITION REPORTS AS ALTERNATIVES TO INCARCERATION.
MORE RECENTLY PATTY BECAME ASSISTANT CHIEF PUBLIC DEFENDER
OVERSEEING THE OFFICE'S DEFENSE DIVISION WHICH INCLUDES
REPRESENTATION IN ADULT JUVENILE IMMIGRATION
POST-CONVICTION AND MENTAL HEALTH CASES.
IN RECENT YEARS, PATTY'S LEADERSHIP WAS CENTRAL TO THE
FIGHT TO CLOSE SAN FRANCISCO'S JUVENILE HALL WHICH REMAINS THE
OFFICE'S NORTH STAR AND HERS. PATTY HAS BEEN A REGIONAL
AND NATIONAL LEADER IN THIS WORK.
CO-DIRECTOR OF THE PACIFIC JUVENILE DEFENDER CENTER
APPOINTED TO OBAMA'S SCIENCE ADVISORY BOARD ON JUVENILE
AND CRIMINAL JUSTICE AND A MEMBER OF THE JUDICIAL
COUNCIL'S FAMILY AND LAW ADVISORY COMMITTEE.
THE CENTER FOR FAMILIES CHILDREN IN THE COURTS AND THE
MCARTHUR RESEARCH NETWORK IN ADOLESCENT DEVELOPMENT
AND JUVENILE JUSTICE. SHE SERVES ON THE BOARDS OF THE
CENTER FOR JUVENILE CRIMINAL JUSTICE AND THE EAST BAY
CHILDREN'S LAW OFFICES. FOR THE PAST EIGHT YEARS SHE'S
ORGANIZED AND FACILITATED QUARTERLY MEETINGS OF
CALIFORNIA'S LEADING JUVENILE JUSTICE ADVOCACY GROUPS.
WORK THAT HAS DRIVEN MAJOR POLICY WINS REDUCING THE
STATE'S YOUTH INCARCERATION RATE.
>> HER HONORS INCLUDE THE SAN FRANCISCO MODERN DAY
ABOLITIONIST AWARD, THE PACIFIC ASIAN AMERICAN WOMEN BAY AREA'S
COALITION WOMAN WARRIOR AWARD, THE NATIONAL JUVENILE DEFENDERS
CENTER LEADERSHIP AWARD, THE PACIFIC JUVENILE DEFENDER OF
THE YEAR AWARD AND THE CALIFORNIA WELLNESS FOUNDATION
PEACE PRIZE. TODAY WE THANK PATTY LEE, THE
49 YEAR FAN FOR 49 YEARS OF FIGHTING FOR THE PEOPLE THE
CITY TOO OFTEN COULD USE TO MOVE AND.
AND PATTY, BEFORE YOU SPEAK. >> WE DO HAVE A SUPERVISOR CHAN
BUT I DO WANT TO BRING UP PUBLIC DEFENDER MINO RASOOL TO
SPEAK AFTER SUPERVISOR CHAN. >> I JUST WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR HONORING YOU.
IT'S YOU DON'T REMEMBER ME BUT I REMEMBER YOU.
>> I WAS YOUNG, A CASE MANAGER FOR A COMMUNITY YOUTH CENTER
SPECIFICALLY FOR MONOLINGUAL YOUTH ON JUVENILE PROBATION
IN NEW IMMIGRANT FAMILIES AND WITH THEIR YOUNG PEOPLE
GOING THROUGH THE SYSTEM YOU WERE BAD.
>> YOU STILL ARE BECAUSE YOU ARE YOU HOLD PEOPLE ACCOUNTABLE
AND BUT YOU ALSO MUCH COMPASSION AND WITH SO MUCH
LOVE AND THAT PEOPLE CAN SEE THAT YOU WANT THE BEST FOR THEM
THE FAMILIES COULD SEE YOU WANTED THE BEST FOR FOR THEIR
KIDS AND THAT WAS REALLY, REALLY IMPORTANT FOR IMMIGRANT
FAMILIES WHO WERE SCARED GOING THROUGH THE SYSTEM.
BUT YOU WERE THERE EVERY STEP OF THE WAY WITH THEM GOING
THROUGH ALL OF IT AS AND THAT'S HOW I THINK I LEARN SO MUCH
FROM YOU FROM THAT POINT AND ON AN UNDERSTANDING WHAT IT MEANS
TO REFORM THE CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM AND WHAT IT MEANS FOR
YOUNG PEOPLE ESPECIALLY STUCK IN STUCK IN THAT SYSTEM
AND WHAT WE CAN DO TO GIVE THEM HOPE AND GIVE THEM A FUTURE
THAT IS MUCH BETTER AND THAT THEY DESERVE THAT TOO AND SO DO
THEIR FAMILIES. SO YOUR WORK IT'S IMPACTFUL.
I KNOW THERE'S GENERATIONS OF YOUNG PEOPLE ONE NIGHT
GENERATIONS ONLY 49 YEARS BUT STILL THAT CENTURY THERE ARE
LIKE A LOT OF YOUNG PEOPLE TODAY HAVING A GREAT FUTURE
BECAUSE OF YOU. THEY OWE IT TO YOU AND SO DO
THEIR FAMILIES. SO FOR THAT WE'RE GRATEFUL.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR WORK.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR KIM.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE. YOU KNOW A SENIOR ATTORNEY
IN THE OFFICE TOLD ME THAT IF WE MADE A LINE IF EVERYONE WHO
DECIDED TO BE A PUBLIC DEFENDER AS A RESULT OF THE INFLUENCE OF
PATTY LEE IT WOULD START HERE. GO OUT THAT DOOR, SNEAK AROUND
AND BE ALL THE WAY OUTSIDE THE INFLUENCE THAT PATTY LEE HAS
HAD ON GENERATIONS OF PUBLIC DEFENDERS IS ABSOLUTELY
INCREDIBLE. SHE'S BEEN A HUGE LEADER IN OUR
FIELD. >> POSITIVELY INFLUENCING THE
LIVES OF THOUSANDS OF SYSTEM INVOLVED PEOPLE.
ONE OF THE MOST EMPATHETIC PEOPLE THAT I'VE EVER MET.
THE LIVING EMBODIMENT OF ONE OF OUR STATED VALUES WHICH IS THAT
OF COMPASSION WHILE STILL ALWAYS BEING A FIGHTER.
>> SHE'S ONE OF THE DEFENDERS THAT BEGAN THE HOLISTIC DEFENSE
MOVEMENT THAT WE TRY TO LIVE UP TO EVERY DAY.
AND WHAT THAT MEANS IS IN ADDITION TO PROTECTING THE
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS IN COURTS AND FIGHTING FOR JUST RESULTS
IN THE COURTROOM, WE MEET PEOPLE IN THEIR FAMILIES AT THE
MOST VULNERABLE PERIOD IN THEIR LIVES.
AND BECAUSE OF THE LEADERSHIP, PEOPLE LIKE PATTY, MANY WHO
HAVE HAD TO ENDURE A COMPLEX TRAUMA, SYSTEMIC RACISM
AND OTHER BARRIERS, WE'RE ABLE TO TRY AND FIND THAT CONNECTION
THAT CONNECTION TO MENTORS. THAT CONNECTION TO TREATMENT
THAT CONNECTION TO THERAPY. THAT CONNECTION TO JOB
OPPORTUNITIES, THAT CONNECTION TO EDUCATION THAT CAN LEAD TO A
MORE POSITIVE TRAJECTORY FOR THOSE WHO WE REPRESENT.
THAT HOLISTIC MODEL HAS BEEN EMULATED BY DEFENDER OFFICES
ACROSS THE COUNTRY. I HAD A TRIAL THAT WE DID
IN THE OFFICE AND IT WAS THE LAST DIRECT FILE ON A YOUNG
PERSON IN ADULT COURT. THE CLIENT WAS IN CUSTODY FOR A
NUMBER OF YEARS VERY COMPLEX TRIAL.
IT TOOK A LONG TIME TO LITIGATE .
ONCE WE FINALLY GOT TO THE JURY THEY ACTUALLY VOTED NOT GUILTY.
IN ABOUT AN HOUR THE CLIENT WAS RELEASED.
BUT I'LL NEVER FORGET WHEN I WALK WITH THAT CLIENT IN THE
OFFICE AND PATTY LOOKED UP AND SAW HIM, SHE IMMEDIATELY
RECOGNIZED HIM, CALLED HIM UP BY HIS NICKNAME AND CAME UP
AND GAVE HIM THE BIGGEST HUG AND FOR HER SHE TREATS ALL OF
HER CLIENTS AS A PART OF HER FAMILY.
AND WHEN WE TRAIN PEOPLE WE ASK, YOU KNOW, WHAT KIND OF
REPRESENTATION WOULD YOU WANT FOR YOUR LOVED ONE IF THEY WERE
IN THE SYSTEM? WELL, THAT'S WHAT WE SHOULD
PROVIDE. BUT FOR PATTY THAT'S NOT AN
EXERCISE BECAUSE SHE REALLY DOES CONSIDER EVERYONE SHE
REPRESENTS AS PART OF HER FAMILY.
SO PATTY, I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR YOUR MENTORSHIP.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR INSPIRATION .
>> THANK YOU FOR ALL OF THE AMAZING WORK FOR OUR CLIENTS
AND YOUR SIMPLY EPIC CAREER AS ONE OF OUR PARALEGALS SAID AS
WE WERE WALKING IN HERE YOU ARE EVERYTHING.
>> AND I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR BEING OUR EVERYTHING TO
EVERYONE FOR SO MANY YEARS AND WE WISH YOU ALL THE BEST
IN YOUR NEXT CHAPTER. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON, YOU TOOK
THE WORDS OUT OF MY MOUTH. >> I AM GOING OUT AS A 49 YEAR
OLD AND AS A DAUGHTER OF SAN FRANCISCO.
SO FIRST BORN AN IMMIGRANT FAMILY PROUDLY A SAN
FRANCISCAN. SO AFTER 49 YEARS IN THE PUBLIC
DEFENDER'S OFFICE I STAND HERE WITH A FULL HEART AND DEEP
GRATITUDE. >> THIS OFFICE OF MONO HAS
MENTIONED AND MY FAMILY BACK HERE HAS BEEN MY HOME.
>> MY COMMUNITY AND MY FAMILY. >> I HAVE HAD THE EXTRAORDINARY
PRIVILEGE OF WORKING ALONGSIDE WITH THE MOST AMAZING PEOPLE
WHO BELIEVE THAT JUSTICE IS ABOUT HUMANITY.
>> IT IS ABOUT COURAGE AND GIVING PEOPLE A CHANCE TO
BE HEARD, TO BE LOVED. >> AND THOSE THAT KNOW ME TO BE
HUGGED IT MAY. >> SO MUCH OF MY CAREER AS YOU
ALL KNOW AND I'VE HAD THIS PRIVILEGE AND AN HONOR
DEDICATED TO FIGHTING FOR YOUTH AND IMAGINING A BETTER SYSTEM
OF JUSTICE AND COMMUNITY TOGETHER.
>> OMEGA JACK. JACK, JACK FOR WHO'S HERE?
MY YOU ALL AND SHOW YOUR FACE IS NOW JUDGE ROGER CHAN, THE
HEAD OF JUVENILE AND FAMILY COURT MY ENTIRE JUVIE FAMILY
UNDER THE LEADERSHIP OF NOW EMILY GOLDMAN.
>> WE HAVE CONTINUED TO FIGHT THE GOOD FIGHT.
AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS BEEN PART OF THAT FIGHT
AND CHALLENGE THE WAY THAT WE TREAT CHILDREN AND THE WAY THAT
WE TREAT FAMILIES. >> WE WORK TO CLOSE YOUTH
PRISON WITH THE WHY A COALITION .
>> AND IT WAS GOVERNOR NEWSOM THAT SIGNED THE LEGISLATION TO
CLOSE DOWN STATE YOUTH PRISON. AND AND I PROUDLY STAY THAT SAN
FRANCISCO HAS BEEN A LEADER IN THE MOVEMENT TO CLOSE
JUVENILE HALL. >> AND THAT HAS BEEN WITH THE
PARTNERSHIP OF THE WARRIORS THAT WE HAVE HERE IN THIS ROOM.
AND THE WARRIORS THAT WE HAVE HERE SITTING ON THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ALL OF YOU AND I, I GIVE TRIBUTE TO OUR FEARLESS
LEADER SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR LEADING THAT CHARGE AS WELL AS
WITH PRIOR SUPERVISOR HILLARY RONEN AND THEIR AIDES CAROL
AND GOOSEN AND TRACY BROWN. >> I SAW HERE EARLIER WE
COULDN'T HAVE DONE IT, YOU KNOW, AND THE MOVEMENT IS STILL
THERE. >> SO WE HAVE CONTINUED TO
FIGHT THE GOOD FIGHT AND WE WILL NEVER GIVE UP.
>> SO ALONG WITH OUR COMMUNITY PARTNER PARTNERS, IT'S
IMPORTANT TO AS WE SIT HERE TODAY TO RECOGNIZE COMMUNITY
BECAUSE THEY ARE WHAT MAKES SAN FRANCISCO AND I WANT TO PAY
TRIBUTE TO THE MAGIC PROGRAMS ARE OUR LEADER BRITTANY FORD
C.J C.J. YOUNG WOMEN'S FREEDOM CENTER
AND MANY OTHERS. WHEN I FIRST JOINED THE YOUTH
DEFENDER UNIT THAT WAS OVER 30 YEARS AGO.
>> WE WERE AT FULL CAPACITY. >> AND WHAT DOES THAT MEAN?
WE HAD MORE THAN 130 YOUTH LOCKED UP.
IT'S 150 BED FACILITY. BUT STAFF FOR ONE THIRD WE HAD
KIDS THAT WERE DOUBLE BUNKED. WE HAD KIDS THAT WERE SLEEPING
ON THE CONCRETE FLOORS. >> THE ENTIRE GIRLS UNIT WAS
FULL. >> AND I'M SO HAPPY TO REPORT
TODAY I'M NOT ECSTATIC THOUGH. >> WE HAVE 30 YOUTH IN CUSTODY
AND TWO GIRLS, SHE SAYS WE CAN DO BETTER.
>> THERE HAVE BEEN MANY OCCASIONS THAT WE'VE HAD NO
GIRLS. AND AS A MOTHER MOTHER OF FOUR
GIRLS I KNOW WE CAN DO BETTER FOR OUR CHILDREN AND FOR OUR
GIRLS. >> THIS IS NOT A MOMENT TO
CELEBRATE. WE CAN AND WE MUST DO BETTER.
>> I URGE ALL OF US IN THIS ROOM AND ESPECIALLY ON THIS
BOARD TO CONTINUE FIGHTING FOR REFORMS THAT RECOGNIZE THAT
YOUNG PEOPLE DESERVE SUPPORT, OPPORTUNITY AND HOPE NOT CAGES.
WE KNOW THAT DOESN'T WORK. >> AND FOR OUR CLIENTS DOWNTOWN
I AM FOREVER AN ADVOCATE AND OKAY, I HAVE ONE BIG
PARTING ASK PLEASE DON'T DEFUND PRETRIAL DIVERSION RIGHT NOW.
>> MY LIFE SAVED HER LIFE CHANGED HER LIFE.
I DIDN'T I DON'T HAVE THIS PERSON TO SAY THANK YOU.
>> I KNOW THAT THIS IS A PROVEN MODEL THAT I KNOW WORKS.
I HAVE WORKED WITH CLIENTS THROUGH THE YEARS THAT ARE
SUCCESS SUCCESSFUL AND CONTRIBUTE MEMBERS OF OUR
COMMUNITY HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO .
>> PRETRIAL DIVERSION HAS RECOGNIZED SUPPORT FROM THE
LEGISLATURE AND LONG STANDING SUPPORT FROM OUR PHILANTHROPIC
PARTNERS. >> SO IF IT AIN'T BROKE, DON'T
FIX IT. >> AND I HAVE BEEN HONORED TO
STAND WITH THOSE WHO BELIEVE THAT TRUE PUBLIC SAFETY COMES
FROM INVESTING IN PEOPLE AND CREATING PATHWAYS FOR
CHANGE AND FOR A BETTER LIFE. AND I KNOW ALL OF YOU DO HERE
SHARE THAT VALUE THESE PRINCIPLES HAVE BEEN THE
GUIDING LIGHT OUR NORTH STAR FOR OUR OFFICE AND OUR TEAM
MEMBERS HERE. AND THAT HAS BEEN THE VISION
FOR OUR LEADERSHIP TEAM. >> SO TO MATT MANNO BECAUSE AS
YOU LISTEN ANGELA CHAN, OUR LEADERSHIP TEAM, I THANK YOU
FOR THE LASTING IMPACT THAT YOU'VE MADE ON THE OFFICE
AND MOST IMPORTANTLY ON THE PEOPLE WE SERVE.
MANNO I WOULD HAVE FOUGHT TOOTH AND NAIL TO STAY AT JUVIE BUT
WHEN MANNO ASKED ME TO COME JOIN AND COME DOWNTOWN, THE
LEADERSHIP TEAM I LEFT MY PERCH AT JUVIE AND IT WAS REALLY AN
OPPORTUNITY TO REINVEST IN THE LIVES OF ALL OUR CLIENTS THAT
ARE ENMESHED IN THIS CRIMINAL INJUSTICE SYSTEM AND AND I WANT
TO ESPECIALLY THANK THE ATTORNEYS AND THE UNSUNG HEROES
IN OUR OFFICE WHO ARE THE SUPPORT STAFF, THE CLERKS, THE
PARALEGALS INVESTED GATORS, THE THE I.T TEAM.
>> WE COULDN'T DO IT WITHOUT THAT FOUNDATION.
I ALWAYS SAY THEY ARE THE ONES THAT HOLD US TOGETHER.
WE CANNOT DO THIS WORK BY OURSELVES.
>> AND SO I LEAVE TODAY AFTER 49 YEARS ALMOST 50 KNOWING THAT
THE HARD WORK CONTINUES YOU I BELIEVE THAT THE NEXT
GENERATION OF FREEDOM FIGHTERS FREEDOM FIGHTERS WILL CARRY
FORWARD THE VISION OF A MORE JUST AND A MORE COMPASSIONATE
SYSTEM. SO I I, I CAN'T THANK ENOUGH MY
FRIENDS, MY COLLEAGUES, THE MANAGERS THAT ALL THESE
MEETINGS WE'VE HAD I HOPE IT'S MADE A DIFFERENCE.
AND MY I HAVE TO SAY MY FAMILY IS HERE.
>> I WANT TO THANK MY BEST FRIEND.
>> I WAS HOPING I WOULDN'T CRY .
>> LEFT MY TISSUES AND MY BEST FRIEND CONFIDANT AND LIFE
PARTNER GILL MY DAUGHTER IS WHO COULDN'T BE HERE CARINA AND YOU
VANESSA AND AUTUMN SAID I'VE GOT FOUR GIRLS.
>> MY GRANDDAUGHTER COCO IS HERE.
I THANK YOU FOR SACRIFICING WIFE MOMMY AND GRANDMA TIME TO
MY ALMOST HALF CENTURY WITH THE PUBLIC DEFENDER'S OFFICE AND TO
MY SISTER JENNY WHO IS HERE AND MY BROTHER JIMMY.
THANK YOU FOR BRINGING THE SPIRIT OF MOM AND DAD TODAY
AND I WANT TO THANK YOU ALL FOR WALKING ALONG SIDE WITH ME
THROUGH THIS AMAZING JOURNEY. >> THE PD'S OFFICE WILL ALWAYS
BE A PART OF WHO I AM. YOU ARE MY FAMILY AND IT HAS
BEEN MY PRIVILEGE AND HONOR TO SERVE.
>> SO I SIGN OFF TODAY I'M STILL ON A FEW FEW BOARDS SO
YOU MAY SEE ME HERE BUT I AM NOT SIGNING OUT.
>> OKAY. I GOT ANOTHER 50 YEARS TO GO
AND SO THANK YOU FOR THIS TIME .
SUPERVISOR WALDEN WOULD YOU LIKE TO BRING PATTY INTO THE
WELL, YOU KNOW WHAT I'M I'M I'M SORRY.
I'M JUST PICTURE AND TAKE A GROUP PICTURE OUTSIDE.
EVERYONE EVERYBODY FROM PATTY BECAUSE THERE'S SOMETHING THERE
. YEAH, I'M AS SOON AS I SEE
INTERESTING I DO THINK ALL RIGHT NEXT UP DISTRICT THREE
SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN COLLEAGUES
TODAY I HAVE THE HONOR OF WELCOMING SHENG T CHEN TO THE
CHAMBERS FOR A SPECIAL RECOGNITION SHANTI WOULD YOU
PLEASE COME UP AND JOIN US? >> LAST MONTH A NUMBER OF US ON
THIS BOARD GATHERED IN A CHINATOWN ALLEY TO CELEBRATE TO
CELEBRATE SHANTI AND SPECIFICALLY HER WORK TO
OPEN THE OUT MUSEUM. WE WERE JOINED BY HUNDREDS OF
OTHERS NEIGHBORS, ARTISTS, ADMIRERS AND SUPPORTERS.
THE OUT MUSEUM'S OPENING IS SIGNIFICANT.
IT IS THE WORLD'S FIRST CHINESE MUSEUM.
>> IT IS ALSO THE REALIZATION OF A DREAM FOR SHANGHAI WHO
SKETCH THE IDEA FOR THE MUSEUM MORE THAN SIX YEARS AGO WHEN
SHE WAS ISOLATED INSIDE HER SHANGHAI APARTMENT DURING THE
PANDEMIC, THE MUSEUM IS A POWERFUL REPRESENTATION OF
STORIES THAT HAVE OFTEN BEEN UNTOLD IN A PHYSICAL SPACE
DEDICATED TO THE COUNTLESS CHINESE IMMIGRANTS WHO HAVE HAD
THEIR STORIES CENSORED OR ERASED SIMPLY ON THE BASIS OF
WHO THEY LOVE. ONE FELLOW ARTIST DESCRIBED
SHANGHAI AS THE MOST COURAGEOUS PERSON SHE KNEW WHILE ANOTHER
GAVE HER PRAISE FOR HER DECISION DETERMINATION TO SEE
THIS VISION THROUGH TO LAST MONTH'S OPENING AND TRUE TO
CHINATOWN IT TAKES A VILLAGE TO BRING AN IDEA TO LIFE
IN PARTICULAR THE CHINESE CULTURE CENTER HAS BEEN A VITAL
EARLY SUPPORTER AND FUNDER OF THIS WORK THE WORLD'S FIRST
CHINESE LGBTQ PLUS MUSEUM OPENING IN OUR CHINATOWN IS A
FITTING MILESTONE AND FEELS LIKE A STORY THAT MIGHT ONLY BE
POSSIBLE IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> SO AS WE CELEBRATE BOTH
PRIDE AND IMMIGRANT HERITAGE MONTH WE APPLAUD YOU.
SHANGHAI FOR HOW YOU'VE ALREADY HELPED SHAPE OUR CITY AND FOR
ALL THAT WE KNOW YOU WILL CONTINUE TO DO.
AND NOW THE FLOOR IS YOURS. IF YOU MIGHT WANT TO SAY A FEW
WORDS THANK YOU. >> GO AHEAD.
CHANGING THE STATUE DAZZLE GOOD LIGHTING FILM AND THEN YOU HAVE
PRIDE
ON THE BROOM. MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF
ADVISERS, DISTINGUISHED GUESTS AND FRIENDS.
GOOD AFTERNOON. I'M A VOLUNTEER AT OUR MUSEUM.
I'M HERE TO TRANSLATE SCIENTISTS SPEECH.
IT IS A GREAT HONOR FOR ME TO RECEIVE THIS RECOGNITION DURING
THE PRIDE MONTH IN JUNE. TODAY I GUESS THAT IS A WAR
WITH HUMILITY. >> AND I DEDICATE IT TO THE
CHINATOWN COMMUNITY THAT DEARLY LOVE AS WELL AS TO MY AND ALL
MY COLLEAGUES VOLUNTEERS AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO HAVE
WORKED ALONGSIDE AND SUPPORTED US.
AND FINALLY LGBTQ MUSEUM OUR MUSEUM WITH THE HOPE TO
PRESERVING AND SHARING THE HISTORY AND CULTURE OF CHINESE
LANGUAGE, LGBTQ COMMUNITIES AND OF CREATING A SPACE FOR
GREATER UNDERSTANDING, RESPECT AND CONNECTION.
THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE WORLD'S FIRST CHINESE LANGUAGE
LGBTQ MUSEUM IN CHINATOWN WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN POSSIBLE WITHOUT
THE SUPPORT OF LOCAL RESIDENTS, BUSINESS AND COMMUNITY
ORGANIZATION AS I HAVE COME TO UNDERSTAND THAT DIVERSITY
AND INCLUSION ARE AMONG THE MOST VALUABLE STRENGTH OF THIS
CITY. >> I WOULD LIKE TO SEE A
RETHINK THIS TIME AS THE SCHOOL BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AS WELL AS
SUPERVISOR DANNY SLAUGHTER OF DISTRICT THREE FOR YOUR
RECOGNITION AND SUPPORT. THIS HONOR DOES NOT BELONG TO
ME ALONE. IT BELONGS TO EVERYONE WHO
BELIEVES IN THE POWER OF COMMUNITY AND HAS CONTRIBUTED
TO IT. I HAVE CONTINUED TO WORK
ALONGSIDE THE CHINATOWN COMMUNITY AND DEDICATE MYSELF.
HOWEVER MODESTLY TO THE PRESERVATION AND ADVANCEMENT OF
CHINESE LANGUAGE, LGBTQ HISTORY, CULTURE AND THE ARTS.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH
. >> DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR
WONG. GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
TODAY I'M PROUD TO RECOGNIZE EMMA SLIM.
WOULD YOU LIKE TO COME UP? >> HER HUSBAND, FATHER,
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY ADVOCATE AND PROUD SAN FRANCISCAN WHOSE
LIFE AND WORK BEAUTIFULLY REFLECT THE SPIRIT OF BOTH
IMMIGRANT HERITAGE MONTH AND PRIDE.
AND THIS CAME FROM TO THE UNITED STATES FROM SINGAPORE
IN 1999 TO BE WITH HIS PARTNER MIKI.
BUT LIKE SO MANY SAME SEX BINATIONAL COUPLES AT THE TIME,
THEY'RE TREATED AS LEGAL STRANGERS UNDER THE LAW WITHOUT
MARRIAGE EQUALITY AND FELT EQUAL IMMIGRATION PROTECTIONS
FOR LGBTQ PLUS FAMILIES. AND WAS QUICKLY SAW THAT HIS
OWN FAMILY'S STRUGGLE WAS PART OF SOMETHING MUCH LARGER.
RATHER THAN ACCEPT THAT INJUSTICE AND MUST HELP
ORGANIZE AGAINST IT, HE CO-FOUNDED OUT FOR IMMIGRATION
AN ALL VOLUNTEER GRASSROOTS ORGANIZATION THAT LIFT UP THE
STORIES OF SAME SEX BINATIONAL COUPLES AND HELPED CONNECT TO
MOVEMENTS THAT HAD TOO OFTEN BEEN KEPT SEPARATE IMMIGRANT
RIGHTS AND THE LGBT Q PLUS COMMUNITY EQUALITY COMMUNITY.
>> AND MOST UNDERSTOOD THAT THESE STRUGGLES WERE DEEPLY
CONNECTED AND THAT OUR COMMUNITIES WOULD BE STRONGER
WHEN WE FOUGHT TOGETHER. THE COMMITMENT TO SERVICE ONLY
GREW AND WAS HELPED ORGANIZE SAN FRANCISCO'S 2007 IMMIGRANT
RIGHTS SUMMIT. >> SERVED ON CITY COMMITTEES
AND ADVISORY BODIES, VOLUNTEERED AT HIS DAUGHTER'S
PUBLIC SCHOOL AND SERVED ON THE BOARD OF LYRIC SUPPORTING LGBTQ
YOUTH IN FINDING SAFETY, BELONGING AND COMMUNITY.
HE ALSO BROUGHT THAT SAME DEDICATION TO CHINESE FOR
AFFIRMATIVE ACTION WHERE HE FOUGHT AGAINST PROPOSITION
EIGHT AND CONTINUES TO SERVE SAN FRANCISCO'S LIMITED ENGLISH
PROFICIENT CHINESE COMMUNITY THROUGH ECONOMIC JUSTICE,
EMPLOYMENT AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT WORK.
AND THIS STORY IS A SAN FRANCISCO STORY.
IT IS ABOUT IMMIGRATION, FAMILY PRIDE, PERSEVERANCE AND THE
BELIEF THAT NO ONE SHOULD HAVE TO CHOOSE BETWEEN WHO THEY LOVE
AND WHERE THEY BELONG. >> SO TODAY DURING IMMIGRANT
HERITAGE MONTH AND PRIDE WE HONOR AL-MUSALLAM FOR HIS
DECADES OF ADVOCACY, COALITION BUILDING AND SERVICE TO A MORE
JUST INCLUSIVE AND WELCOMING SAN FRANCISCO.
>> CONGRATULATIONS, AMOS AND THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. >> I DIDN'T PREPARE A SPEECH.
I DIDN'T KNOW I'M SUPPOSED TO MAKE A SPEECH BUT THIS IS A
DEEP HONOR. I ARRIVE HERE MAY 1999 SO THIS
IS MY 27TH YEAR HERE. SAN FRANCISCO HAS GIVEN ME MY
POLITICAL VOICE, MY ACTIVISM. IT HAS AFFIRMED THAT I HAVE A
PLACE IN THIS CITY AS AN IMMIGRANT, AS A GAY PERSON.
IT HAS ALLOWED ME TO ADOPT A DAUGHTER FROM THE CITY.
AND MY MIND IS STILL BLOWN THAT SHE JUST GRADUATED FROM
MCCAULEY INSTITUTE A MONTH AGO .
SO I AM OVERWHELMED TO BE STANDING HERE AS SOMEBODY WHO
DIDN'T HAVE A POLITICAL VOICE WHEN I WAS GROWING UP, DIDN'T
KNOW HOW TO FIGHT FOR OTHER PEOPLE, HOW TO ADVOCATE FOR
ISSUES THAT ARE IMPORTANT TO ME TO COME HERE TO BE ABLE TO MEET
FELLOW VOLUNTEERS, FELLOW JOURNEYMEN TO FIGHT FOR A
DIVERSE SOCIETY, TO FIGHT FOR SERVICES AND HELP FOR
RECOGNITION FOR IMMIGRANTS AND THEIR CONTRIBUTION TO THIS
COUNTRY AND RIGHT NOW HELPING LIMITED ENGLISH PROFICIENT
COMMUNITY MEMBERS LOOK FOR JOBS .
YOU HAVE GIVEN ME A NEW LIFE. YOU HAVE GIVEN ME THE
UNDERSTANDING ABOUT WHAT IT IS TO HELP OTHERS.
YOU HAVE GIVEN ME ULTIMATE, ULTIMATE STRESS
AND SATISFACTION HAVING TO FIGHT FOR THE PEOPLE WHO
DOESN'T HAVE A VOICE TO EMPOWER THEM, TO EDUCATE THEM AND TO
GIVE THEM A NEW PATH. I'M NOT HERE ALONE.
I HAVE MY FAMILIES MY LOVING HUSBAND WHO SUPPORTED ME EVEN
WHILE WE ARE SEPARATED ON TWO DIFFERENT COUNTRIES TO HIM
BRINGING ME OVER ME GETTING A DEGREE HERE MY MASTERS HERE,
FINDING MY POLITICAL VOICE AND FINDING WHAT I CAN DO WITH
MY VOICE AND HOW TO EMPOWER PEOPLE TO GIVE THEM MORE VOICE
TO FIGHT FOR THEMSELVES. HAS BEEN A JOY HAS BEEN A
REWARD THAT KEPT COMING. I APPRECIATE THIS RECOGNITION
VERY, VERY, VERY MUCH. I'M REALLY OVERWHELMED TO BE
SPEAKING TO ALL OF YOU. I AM TOTALLY AFRAID OF TALKING
TO LEADERS. IF YOU SEE ME AT EVENTS YOU
KNOW I RUN AWAY BECAUSE I DON'T KNOW YOU ARE JUST PEOPLE UP
THERE THAT I NEED TO RESPECT BECAUSE YOU ARE THE PEOPLE THAT
FIGHT FOR US. AND I APPRECIATE YOUR PASSION
IN THIS JOB AND I WOULD LIKE TO OFFER YOU SOME COMMENDATION FOR
YOUR FIGHT. WE ARE AT A POINT WHERE WE ARE
UNDER ATTACK AND YOU KNOW WE NEED YOUR SUPPORT.
THE CITY AND YOU SUPPORT THE DIVERSE COMMUNITY AND NEED YOUR
SUPPORT. AND ON BEHALF OF ALL OF THEM I
WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR THIS AWESOME, AWESOME HONOR
AND PRIVILEGE. >> THANK YOU TO THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT. AND LASTLY BUT NOT LEAST FOR
THIS PRIDE TUESDAY WE'RE GOING TO HONOR SOME ALLIES.
I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE TERRY ASTON BENNETT TO COME UP
AND MARTHA TO COME UP AND RICH TO COME UP AND WE'LL REALLY
ANYBODY YOU WANT TO BRING UP TO COME UP BECAUSE FRIENDS TODAY
WE'RE GOING TO HONOR ONE OF THE QUEEREST BUSINESSES THERE IS
CLIFFS VARIETY ON THE OCCASION THIS YEAR IS THEIR 90TH
ANNIVERSARY YEAR AND AND I'M GOING TO TELL YOU A LITTLE BIT
ABOUT THE HISTORY. IN 1936 HILARIA DE BARCA A
FORMER SCHOOLTEACHER FROM NEW MEXICO OPENED THE VERY FIRST
CLIFFS AS THE MOSTLY ONE MAN SHOP AT 545.
CASTRO IN A QUIET LITTLE NEIGHBORHOOD THEN KNOWN AS
EUREKA VALLEY. HE NAMED IT AFTER HIS YOUNGEST
SON CLIFFORD AND SOLD MAGAZINES CIGARS, SEWING NOTIONS
AND CANDY. IN 1942, HILARIO MOVED CLIFFS
FROM 545 CASTRO TO 515 CASTRO AND THE SECOND SHOP WAS STILL
QUITE SMALL BUT ACTUALLY DOUBLE THE SIZE OF THE ORIGINAL
LOCATION. IN 1946 HILARIA'S SON ERNIE
JOINED THE BUSINESS. HE WOULD BRING BIG CHANGES SOON
AFTER JOINING HE LAUNCHED THE FIRST HALLOWEEN STREET PARTY ON
CASTRO STREET WHICH BEGAN AS A CHILDREN'S COSTUME CONTEST WITH
A SINGLE STOOL FOR A STAGE AND GREW OVER THE DECADES INTO
A NEIGHBORHOOD INSTITUTION. ERNIE WAS AN INVENTOR AND AN
ENTREPRENEUR AND THE SECOND LOCATION WAS THE BIRTHPLACE OF
MANY OF HIS INNOVATIONS. HE GOT CREATIVE WITH LITTLE
SPACE. HE HAD TO WORK WITH THE
CEILING. HE BUILT A MOTORIZED CANDY
DISPLAY WHICH INCLUDED METAL TRAYS SUSPENDED ON BICYCLE
CHAIN TRACKS DESCENDING TO THE CUSTOMER'S REACH AT THE FLIP OF
A SWITCH. HE FOLLOWED IT WITH SIMILAR
MACHINES FOR SEWING RIBBONS, BUTTONS, KEY BLANKS, GREETING
CARDS AND FABRIC DYES. THE RIBBON MACHINE IS STILL
RUNNING IN THE ANNEX TODAY. >> THESE INNOVATIONS REALLY
GREW THE BUSINESS BUT UNFORTUNATELY THE PROPERTY
OWNER, THE HIBERNIA BANK DEMOLISHED THE SECOND LOCATION
SO THEY COULD BUILD A DRIVE THRU TELLER FOR THEIR BANK.
>> IN 1960 CLIFF'S VARIETY OPENED THEIR THIRD LOCATION AT
495 CASTRO AND THIS CAME TO BE KNOWN AS THE STORE WHERE YOU
COULD TAKE ANYTHING TO BE REPAIRED BECAUSE ERNIE WOULD
FIX IT. BEGINNING IN 1963, ERNIE ASTON
ERNIE DE BARCA'S GRANDSON AND HILARIA'S GREAT GRANDSON
STARTED WORKING AT CLIFF'S AFTER SCHOOL.
NOW MARTHA SULLIVAN, ERNIE'S GIRLFRIEND STARTED WORKING AT
CLIFF'S IN 1968. SHE MARRIED ERNIE A YEAR LATER,
TOOK OVER THE BOOKS AND HAS NEVER LEFT.
>> AT APPLAUSE AT 77 AFTER 58 YEARS WORKING THERE SHE SO
SHOWS NO SIGNS OF SLOWING DOWN .
>> NOW THE HISTORY OF THE CASTRO EUREKA THAT FORMERLY
EUREKA VALLEY NOW CASTRO IN THE 60S AND 70S IS WELL KNOWN BY
THE LATE 60S HIPPIES FROM THE SUMMER OF LOVE HAD BEGUN
TRICKLING OVER THE HILLS TO EUREKA VALLEY AND A FEW GAY
OWNED BUSINESSES WERE OPENING ON CASTRO AS AND LESBIANS
BEGAN BUYING AND INVESTING IN THE OLDER VICTORIANS
AND MORE PEOPLE MOVED INTO THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
COMMERCIAL RENTS INCREASED AND WHEN THE LANDLORD AT THEIR
THIRD LOCATION TRIPLED THE RENT IN 1971, ERNIE DIDN'T
NEGOTIATE. HE BOUGHT THE BUILDING A COUPLE
DOORS DOWN AT 479 CASTRO OUTRIGHT AND CLIFF'S HAS BEEN
THERE EVER SINCE. >> YEAH AS THE NEIGHBORHOOD
CHANGED, CLIFFS CHANGED WITH IT.
THE STORE BECAME THE FIRST STRAIGHT OWNED BUSINESS ON THE
BLOCK TO HIRE OPENLY GAY EMPLOYEES.
>> IT EXPANDED ITS INVENTORY TO MEET THE NEEDS OF THE LGBT Q
PLUS COMMUNITY CONTINUING TO CARRY HARDWARE SUPPLIES.
OF COURSE. >> BUT ADDING RHINESTONE TIARAS
AND BOAS AND WIGS THROUGH THE AIDS CRISIS, THROUGH
RECESSIONS, THROUGH THE RISE OF CHAIN RETAIL AND A GLOBAL
PANDEMIC. CLIFF STAYED OPEN AND FAMILY
RUN. >> MARTHA AND ERNIE'S DAUGHTER
TERRY GREW UP WORKING IN THE SALES FLOOR IN THE FAMILY
TRADITION. SHE CAME BACK AFTER COLLEGE,
TOOK OVER OPERATIONS AND HAS LED THE STORE FOR MORE THAN TWO
DECADES AND IN HER FREE TIME HAS SERVED AS PRESIDENT OF THE
CASTRO MERCHANTS ASSOCIATION MULTIPLE TIMES AS VOLUNTEER TO
ANNUALLY AS AN AIDS LIFECYCLE ROADIE AND AND HAS CONTINUED TO
CARRY HER GREAT GREAT GRANDFATHER'S LEGACY FORWARD.
>> IN 2003 TERRY HAD A DAUGHTER OF HER OWN WHO MAY 1ST DAY BE
THE SIXTH GENERATION TO RUN THE PLACE.
OF COURSE THE FAMILY HAS NOT DONE IT ALONE.
PAUL ELLIS HAS BEEN THE STORE'S MANAGER FOR 40 YEARS STARTING
ON THE SALES FLOOR AND BRINGING IN EXPERTISE IN COSTUME DESIGN,
TEXTILES AND SEWING THAT HAS MADE HIM A TRUSTED RESOURCE FOR
GENERATIONS OF CUSTOMERS AND COWORKERS.
>> JEFFREY GALLEGOS HAS BEEN THERE FOR 30.
THERE WE ARE HAS BEEN THERE 35 YEARS AS A RECEIVING CLERK
WORKING BEHIND THE SCENES WITH GENEROSITY AND MAKES EVERYONE
AROUND HIM FEEL AT HOME. >> MARK WILSON HAS BEEN WITH
CLIFF'S FOR 30 YEARS MOVING FROM THE SALES FLOOR TO THE
BUYING US TO THE BACKROOM WITH METICULOUS ATTENTION TO
EVERYTHING HE TOUCHES. TAMLYN SANGALANG HAS WORKED AS
A SALES CLERK AND LOCKSMITH FOR 33 YEARS SINCE ARRIVING IN SAN
FRANCISCO THROUGH THE TIBETAN RESETTLEMENT PROGRAM.
TOGETHER THE TEAM HAS AND HAS ACCUMULATED MORE THAN 196 YEARS
OF SERVICE TO THE CASTRO COMMUNITY AND THOSE ARE JUST
THE LONGEST SERVING EMPLOYEES. >> SO TERRY AND MARTHA, ON
BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN THE CASTRO
NEIGHBORHOOD. WE ARE ALWAYS AND INCREDIBLY
GRATEFUL TO YOU. CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR 90
YEARS. WE ALSO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE
TERRY'S HUSBAND RICH WHO DID NOT GET A SPECIAL YEAR WHILE HE
GETS APPLAUSE BUT NOT BUT NOT A SPECIAL SHOUT OUT BECAUSE HE'S
A RELATIVELY JUNIOR, YOU KNOW, EMPLOYEE THERE AT ONLY 20
YEARS. >> SO YOU KNOW CATCH UP TERRY.
>> THE FLOOR IS YOURS. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
I CAN'T PROMISE ANYTHING ABOUT CAMILLE BECAUSE I LIKE MY CHILD
AND RETAIL'S REALLY HARD THESE DAYS.
>> WE HAVE BEEN VERY GRATEFUL AT CLIFF'S TO HAVE A
RELATIONSHIP WITH OUR NEIGHBORHOOD SUPERVISORS GOING
BACK TO GOING BACK TO HARVEY MILK.
REALLY? HE'S ACTUALLY THE ONLY
POLITICAL CANDIDATE WE'VE EVER ENDORSED BUT A DISTRICT DATE
HAS A REALLY SPECIAL RELATIONSHIP WITH CITY HALL
THAT OUR DISTRICT SUPERVISOR MAKES A POINT OF BEING AT OUR
MONTHLY MERCHANT MEETINGS AND MAKES A POINT OF HAVING
RELATIONSHIPS WITH THE NEIGHBORHOOD BUSINESSES
AND THAT IS SUCH AN INTEGRAL PART OF MAKING SURE THAT ALL
THE BUSINESSES THAT YOU LOVE AND WANT TO SEE SUCCEED HAVE A
CHANCE BECAUSE MOST OF US IN OUR DAY TO DAY LIVES DON'T
HAVE TIME TO SEND EMAILS AND PICK UP PHONES TO CALL
AND SAY HEY YOU DOUBLED MY GROSS RECEIPTS TAXES THIS YEAR
WHICH YOU DID. >> BUT THAT RELATIONSHIP MAKES
IT POSSIBLE FOR THE THINGS THAT WOULD OTHERWISE TAKE DOWN
BUSINESSES LIKE MINE TO SUCCEED.
SO FOR THAT I'M INCREDIBLY GRATEFUL BUT MORE GRATEFUL AM I
TO ALL THE AIDES THAT WORK IN HIS OFFICE BECAUSE WE ALL
KNOW THAT THE AIDES ARE THE ONES THAT REALLY DO THE WORK.
TRUE. I WOULD LIKE TO GIVE A SPECIAL
SHOUT OUT TO ADAM WHO WORKED REALLY HARD TO MAKE DISTRICT
EIGHT A SPECIAL PLACE AND TO SEE US AND BE HEARD AND TO
SOPHIE WHO IS AN INCREDIBLE PERSON AND I HOPE WHOEVER
REPLACES YOU HAS THE GOOD SENSE TO HIRE HER.
>> YES. >> BUT THANK YOU SO MUCH
AND WE'LL JUST KEEP KEEP IT ON AS LONG AS WE CAN.
>> BLUE LIVES JUST ALWAYS MAKING SIDE
. IS THERE GOING TO BE PUBLIC
COMMENT OR. >> ALL RIGHT.
WITH THAT LET'S GO BACK TO ROLL CALL AND I BELIEVE WE WERE AT
SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT IN A THANK YOU.
>> SO IN CELEBRATION OF PRIDE IT IS MY HONOR TO STAND
IN SOLIDARITY WITH BOTH OUR LGBTQ AND LABOR COMMUNITIES TO
INTRODUCE A RESOLUTION TO CELEBRATE THE ANNIVERSARY OF
THE COURSE BOYCOTT HIGHLIGHTING THE HISTORIC PARTNERSHIP
BETWEEN LGBTQ RIGHTS AND ORGANIZED LABOR MOVEMENTS
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO IN THE 1960, CHICANO AND BLACK
ORGANIZERS BEGAN A BOYCOTT THE COURSE BREWERY THE COURSE
BREWERY COMPANY IN COLORADO IN PROTEST AGAINST THE
COMPANIES DISCRIMINATE TORY HIRING PRACTICES TO
SYSTEMATICALLY SCREEN OUT BLACK, CHICANO AND LGBTQ
WORKERS. >> AT ONE POINT THE BEER
COMPANY EVEN SUBJECTED WORKERS TO MANDATORY POLYGRAPH TESTS
PRYING INTO WORKERS PERSONAL LIVES AND ASKING INTRUDING
QUESTIONS REGARDING THEIR SEXUAL ORIENTATION GENDER
IDENTITY AND POLITICAL AND RELIGIOUS BELIEFS.
IN 1977 THE BOYCOTT MOVEMENT WAS GALVANIZING CALIFORNIA WHEN
A HISTORIC ALLIANCE WAS FORGED IN SAN FRANCISCO BETWEEN
ORGANIZED LABOR AND LGBTQ COMMUNITY.
THE ALLIANCE WAS LED BY PRESIDENT ALLAN BAIRD AND ANDY
CIRCLES OF TEAMSTERS LOCAL 9 TO 1 AND LGBTQ RIGHTS ACTIVIST
HARVEY MILK AND HOWARD WALLACE STANDING AGAINST CORPORATE
DISCRIMINATION. THEY LAUNCH A LARGE SCALE
BOYCOTT FROM THE CASTRO'S DISTRICT WHICH LATER SPREAD
THROUGH THE BAY AREA AND CALIFORNIA DUE TO THE
STATEWIDE EFFORT. THE BEER COURSE BREWERY COMPANY
THEIR MARKET SHARE IN CALIFORNIA PLUMMETED FROM
40% TO ABOUT 14% IN THE 1970S. BY 1987 COURSE WAS FORCED TO
ADOPT SOME OF THE FIRST CORPORATE NONDISCRIMINATION
POLICY IN THE COUNTRY. THE COURSE BOYCOTTS REMINDS US
THAT THE STRUGGLE FOR LABOR RIGHTS IS IN SEPARABLE FROM THE
STRUGGLE FOR CIVIL RIGHTS, THE FIGHT FOR THE BETTERMENT OF OUR
MOST VULNERABLE MEMBERS OF SOCIETY CAN ONLY BE ACHIEVED
WHEN WE CONTINUE TO UPLIFT EACH OTHER IN OUR MUTUAL FIGHTS THAT
EXIST TO THRIVE AND TO BE LOVED.
SO THANK YOU HARVEY MILK LGBTQ DEMOCRATIC CLUB CASTRO LGBTQ
CULTURAL DISTRICT TEAMSTERS SAN FRANCISCO LABOR COUNCIL FOR
YOUR PARTNERSHIP ON THIS RESOLUTION AND TO END THE
COMMEMORATIVE POUR OUT EVENT THIS FRIDAY JUNE 26 IN FRONT OF
THE HISTORIC TWIN PEAKS TAVERN AND I'M REALLY HONORED TO BE
INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION TODAY IS CERTAINLY IS A
PRIVILEGE SO AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN SUPERVISE HER CHEN SUBMIT THANK
YOU AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER
THAT INCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES
YOU ALL TO PROVIDE YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT IF YOU LINE UP
ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE
MINUTES AS PRESENTED ITEMS 14 AND 15 ON THE ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE AND OTHER GENERAL MATTERS NOT PUBLISHED
ON THE AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD'S SUBJECT
MATTER JURISDICTION. IF YOU'RE STANDING AT THE TALL
PODIUM YOU'LL NOTICE THERE IS A TIMER WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER
FOR TWO MINUTES PER PERSON. ALL RIGHT, LET'S HEAR FROM OUR
FIRST SPEAKER. >> WELCOME.
THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS AISHA MCCAIN. TODAY IS MY BROTHER ERIC
MCCAIN'S BIRTHDAY AND TODAY THE CITY RELEASED A REPORT FROM A
CIVIL GRAND JURY ON THE FAILURES IN OVERSIGHT.
ERIC ERIC HIS STORY IN THE CHRONICLE AND MY ADVOCACY SINCE
HIS DEATH READING THAT REPORT MADE ME REALLY SAD BECAUSE I
MISS MY BROTHER BUT I ALSO FELT HOPE, YOU KNOW, FOR IT TO COME
OUT ON HIS BIRTHDAY COMING TO THESE BOARD MEETINGS
AND OVERSIGHT MEETINGS HASN'T BEEN EASY.
MY BROTHER'S PREVENTABLE DEATH WAS ONE OF THE MOST PAINFUL
AND DIFFICULT, DIFFICULT EXPERIENCES OF MY LIFE
ADVOCATING FOR ACCOUNTABILITY WHILE FIGHTING CANCER
AND NAVIGATING MY OWN HEALTH CHALLENGES IS EXHAUSTING.
BUT I KEEP SHOWING UP BECAUSE OF MY BROTHER'S LIFE MATTERED
AND I CAN'T CHANGE WHAT HAPPENED TO ERIC BUT I CAN
CREATE CHANGE FOR OTHER PEOPLE .
SO I'M HERE TO ASK THE BOARD TO TAKE THIS REPORT SERIOUSLY.
PLEASE ACT ON IT. IMPLEMENT ITS RECOMMENDED
ACTIONS. USE THIS MOMENT TO STRENGTHEN
OVERSIGHT ACCOUNTABILITY AND RESIDENT SAFETY.
IT SHOULDN'T TAKE A GRIEVING SISTER AN INVESTIGATIVE
JOURNALIST FOR THE CITY TO ACT .
>> THE BEST WAY TO HONOR MY BROTHER I'M SORRY IT'S OKAY IS
TO ENSURE IT LEADS TO MEANINGFUL CHANGE.
HIS DEATH AND ALL THIS EVERYTHING.
>> MY HOPE IS THAT ERIC'S LEGACY IS NOT ABOUT HIS DEATH.
MY HOPE IS THAT HIS LEGACY IS WHAT CHANGED IN HIS NAME.
>> WHEN I FIRST STARTED SPEAKING I TOLD THEM THEY GOT
THE RIGHT SISTER AND I MEANT EVERY WORD OF THAT.
SO I'M ASKING THIS BOARD TO JUST ACT ON THIS REPORT THAT
WAS ISSUED BY THE CIVIL GRAND JURY.
MAKE THESE CHANGES BUT YOU WANT ACCOUNTABLE.
FOLLOW THE MONEY. WATCH THE MONEY.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR ALLOWING ME TO SPEAK AND HAPPY BIRTHDAY
ERIC. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
BEFORE THE NEXT SPEAKER MAY I JUST ASK THERE IS AN APPROVED
BOARD RULE. THERE ARE NO SOUNDS AUDIBLE
SOUNDS OF SUPPORT OR BEING AGAINST ANY MATTER BUT IF YOU
WANT TO SHOW YOUR SUPPORT YOU'RE WELCOME TO SHOW YOUR
HANDS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS TORY.
I'M A COMMUNITY MEMBER AND AN ADVOCATE FOR THE PRESERVATION
OF BLACK HISTORY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
YESTERDAY MANY OF US ATTENDED A MEETING EXPECTING ANSWERS ABOUT
THE FUTURE OF OUR LITTLE COMMUNITY CENTER.
>> INSTEAD WE WERE ONCE AGAIN ASKED WHAT WE WANT AND NEED
FROM THE VERY INSTITUTIONS THAT PLAYED A ROLE IN DISMANTLING
WHAT WAS ONCE A THRIVING BLACK COMMUNITY.
MANY RESIDENTS ARE TIRED OF ATTENDING MEETING AFTER MEETING
WITHOUT RECEIVING CLEAR ANSWERS .
TRUST IS ALREADY FRAGILE BECAUSE OF THE HISTORY,
DISPLACEMENT, BROKEN PROMISES AND LACK OF TRANSPARENCY IN THE
WESTERN TRADITION. MANY COMMUNITY MEMBERS REMAIN
CONCERNED THAT DESPITE THE DEPARTURE OF CERTAIN
ORGANIZATIONS FROM EARLIER WATCH INDIVIDUALS WITH
LONGSTANDING TIES TO THOSE ORGANIZATIONS CONTINUE TO
OPERATE IN THE BUILDING THROUGH OTHER PROGRAMS.
WHETHER THESE CONCERNS ARE JUSTIFIED OR NOT, THE PUBLIC
DESERVES TRANSPARENCY AND CLEAR ANSWERS ABOUT WHO IS
INFLUENCING THE DECISIONS REGARDING THE FUTURE OF THIS
IMPORTANT COMMUNITY ASSET. THE COMMUNITY DESERVES TO KNOW
WHO IS MAKING DECISIONS, WHAT SAFEGUARDS ARE IN PLACE TO
ENSURE TRANSPARENCY AND HOW RESIDENTS WILL HAVE MEANINGFUL
INPUT IN THE FUTURE OF ELIHU HUTCH COMMUNITY CENTER.
FOR THESE REASONS I'M ASKING THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO
INITIATE LANDMARK DESIGNATION FOR A LARGE COMMUNITY CENTER.
THIS BUILDING IS MORE THAN A FACILITY.
IT IS A SYMBOL OF BLACK SAN FRANCISCO HISTORY, RESILIENCE
AND CULTURAL LEGACY. OUR COMMUNITY DESERVES MORE
THAN LISTENING SESSIONS. RESIDENTS IN THE WESTERN
TRADITION DESERVE REAL ANSWERS. ACCOUNTABILITY AND PROTECTION
OF THIS HISTORIC INSTITUTION FOR GENERATIONS TO COME.
>> AND I AM ABSOLUTELY AND MY BECAUSE THE SAME THE SAME AREA.
>> THESE PEOPLE WERE TOO LITERALLY BEING BILLIONAIRES
HAD THE GOVERNMENT WOULD NEVER CAME IN AND DESTROYED THE
HOUSES. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO. SO I'VE BEEN SUPPORTING THE
PEOPLE'S BUDGET COALITION FIGHTING AGAINST THE MAYORS
DETRIMENTAL PROPOSED CUTS. I HAVE BEFORE SARCASTICALLY
TOLD THE BOARD AND MAYOR TO ASK YOUR CORPORATE AND BILLIONAIRE
FRIENDS FOR DONATIONS. >> AND I COMPLETELY FORGOT
ABOUT THE WHOLE BE TESTED PAYMENT WAIVER THING.
AND SO YOU HAVE BEEN RIGHT. COINCIDENTALLY THE CHRONICLE
PUT OUT A STORY TODAY IN A CITY FULL OF BILLIONAIRES LORI TAP
$7 MILLION IN PRIVATE FUNDS FOR S.F. SUPPORTING SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING REPAIRS AS PUBLIC FUNDS SHRINK.
>> STILL, I HAVE TO ASK WHERE IS THE MONEY FROM ALL OF THESE
BEHEST AND WAIVERS THIS PAST YEAR?
WHERE'S THE TRANSPARENCY? CAN WE GET MORE REPORTING ON
THIS? WE NEED AN EXPLANATION OR AN
INVESTIGATION. AND HERE IS AN INCOMPLETE LIST
OF WAIVERS THAT WERE GRANTED THIS PAST YEAR OR SO.
WE HAVE THE TEMPORARY SHELTER AND HOMELESS SERVICES BEHEST A
PAYMENT WAIVER ENACTED IN OCTOBER THE 24TH 2020 FOR
THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZE THE OFFICE OF THE MAYOR AND THE
DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING TO
SOLICIT DONATIONS FROM VARIOUS PRIVATE ENTITIES
AND ORGANIZATIONS TO SUPPORT THE EXPANSION OF TEMPORARY
SHELTER AND OTHER HOMELESS SERVICES TO SUPPORT PEOPLE
EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS. >> AND THEN WE HAVE ANOTHER ONE
FOR HOMELESS SERVICES BUT AUTHORIZING THE DEPARTMENT OF
HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR,
CHIEF DEPUTIES, DEPUTY DIRECTORS AND PROGRAM
DIRECTORS. >> THIS WAS ENACTED APRIL 20,
25 RENEWED DECEMBER 2025 SEEMS TO BE UNDER RENEWAL AGAIN.
AND THEN WE HAVE FUNDRAISING FOR SERVICES RELATED TO
IMMIGRATION AND LGBTQ PLUS RIGHTS, ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTIONS, REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS, RACIAL EQUITY ENACTED
FEBRUARY 20TH, 25 RENEWED OCTOBER 20TH, 25 AUTHORIZING A
LOT OF IMPORTANT PEOPLE. OFFICE OF THE MAYOR OFFICE OF
THE CITY ATTORNEY OFFICE OF THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR.
THE HEADS OF EACH DIVISION OFFICE DEPARTMENT UNDER THE
SUPERVISION OF THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR TO SOLICIT
DONATIONS. EVEN THE ASSESSOR RECORDER IN A
DIFFERENT RESOLUTION. AND THE DEPUTY ASSESSORS THE
DIRECTOR OF POLICY GOVERNMENT AFFAIRS BLAH BLAH BLAH BLAH.
>> WE'RE ALSO AUTHORIZED TO DO IT.
SO WHERE IS THE MONEY FOR. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LIAM MCGEEVER. ALL RIGHT.
SO WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> AS YOU KNOW, MY NAME IS RICHARD S.G. PETERSON.
>> BOARD PRESIDENT MAN ROOM AND BOARD MEMBERS.
ONCE AGAIN I NOTICE THE ABSENCE OF THE CHAIR FOR DISTRICT NINE.
APPARENTLY FROM WHAT I'M READING IN THE NEWS SHE'S QUITE
HEALTHY AND SHOULD BE HERE TODAY.
I'M NOT FEELING WELL TODAY AND I HAD TO DRAG MYSELF AND I
MADE IT LATE TO THE MEETING. BUT I'M HERE.
BUT WHAT I WANT TO REALLY COMPLAIN ABOUT IS WHY AM I
BEING DISTRACT DID BY AN APPARENT ATTEMPT TO DISBAR ME.
HEY, I'M AN OLD GUY. I'M 83.
WHY DO YOU WANT TO DISBAR ME? I'M STILL A DECENT ATTORNEY.
I CAN PRACTICE LAW BUT ALL OF A SUDDEN MY OWN BAR ASSOCIATION
SENDS MY EMERGENCY CHECK TO PAY MY BAR FEES UP TO ZERO.
>> THE COUNTY. YOU'VE SEEN THE NEWS.
THERE WAS A FOUR PAGE ARTICLE ABOUT SIERRA COUNTY.
NOW AM I SUPPOSED TO BE PARANOID?
>> NO, I DON'T KNOW. MAYBE I AM.
MAYBE I'M NOT. MAYBE THIS IS JUST OH, AN
INNOCENT MISTAKE. HOW MANY INNOCENT MISTAKES ARE
WE GOING TO CONTINUE TO DO? OKAY, I GOT 20S LEFT.
BUT I WANT TO KNOW YOU THAT THERE IS SOMETHING GOING ON
THAT IS VERY DEEP AND THERE'S VERY DIRE CONSEQUENCES
NATIONALLY AND INTERNATIONALLY AND TO OUR OWN DEMOCRACY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
HI. >> GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS STEVE ARENAS.
I'M A RANK AND FILE MEMBER AND STEWARD OF TEAMSTERS LOCAL
853 AND A CO-FOUNDER OF THE CRS BOYCOTT COMMEMORATION COMMITTEE
. I WANT TO COMMEND THIS BOARD
FOR THE CONSIDERATION OF THE RESOLUTION THAT SUPERVISOR CHAN
REFERENCED. TO COMMEMORATE THE CRS BOYCOTT
OFFICIALLY IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THANK YOU FOR BRINGING THIS FORWARD, SUPERVISOR CHAN.
IT'S DEEPLY APPRECIATED. THIS HISTORY IS NOT ONLY
IMPORTANT TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA AND NORTHERN
CALIFORNIA BUT TO THE ENTIRETY OF OUR LABOR MOVEMENT.
IT'S VERY NEAR AND DEAR AND PERSONAL TO ME.
>> AND I WANT TO EXTEND MY PERSONAL THANKS FOR ALL OF YOU
THAT SUPPORT THIS HISTORY THAT ARE IN THE ROOM TODAY AND ALL
OF MY COLLEAGUES IN LABOR AND IN THE COMMUNITY THAT DO AS
WELL. I ONLY WISH THAT HOWARD
WALLACE, HARVEY MILK, ANDY SERWER, KELLIS AND ALAN BAIRD
WERE HERE TO SEE HOW FAR THIS HISTORY HAS COME AND HOW FAR
IT'S GOING TO GO. WITH YOUR HELP AND EVERYBODY'S
HELP IN THE COMMUNITY AND IN LABOR.
SO THANK YOU ALL AGAIN. >> APPRECIATE IT.
AND SOLIDARITY. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO, MY NAME IS NICHOLAS CURRENT.
I WE'LL TALK FROM THE CAUSE BOYCOTT COMMEMORATION COMMITTEE
. YEAH, THIS HISTORY IS REALLY
IMPORTANT. ABOUT TEN YEARS AGO MY SISTER
WAS LIVING IN TRUCKEE. >> WE'RE WORKING FOR CAL FIRE
BUT SHE WOULD DRIVE DOWN TO VISIT HER PARTNER IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND SHE HAD WENT TO A BAR AND TRIED TO ORDER A COURSE
AND THE BARTENDER WAS LIKE WE DON'T SELL CAUSE AND IT WASN'T
LIKE A WE DON'T CARE CAUSE IT'S LIKE WE DON'T SELL IT IN A
PASSIONATE SORT OF WAY AND MY SISTER WAS INTERESTED AND SHE
KNEW THAT I KIND OF WAS CONNECTED WITH THIS BOYCOTT
AND KIND OF KNEW ABOUT IT. SO SHE CALLED ME AND WE TALKED
A LONG TIME BECAUSE THE STORY AND THE LESSON OF THIS HISTORY
IS JUST SO BIG, SO VAST AND WE WE STILL CONTINUE TO TALK ABOUT
IT. BUT I THINK AND WHAT I'VE SEEN
IS THAT MY SISTER NOW IS A SAN FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTER AND MY
OTHER SISTER IS A NURSE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THEY ARE BOTH
REALLY PROUD MEMBERS, UNION MEMBERS AND THEY UNDERSTAND
THAT STRUGGLE NOW WHEREAS BEFORE THEY DID IT AND YEAH IT
JUST TEACHES SO MUCH. SO THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME
AND YOUR CONSIDERATION. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
MANDEL AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS STEVEN TORRES. I'M THE PROGRAM MANAGER FOR THE
CASTRO LGBTQ CULTURAL DISTRICT AND I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO THANK
SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR INTRODUCING THIS LEGISLATION AND TO BROTHER
ARENAS FROM THE TEAMSTERS FOR REALLY DRIVING THIS INITIATIVE
. IT'S PRIDE.
WE SEE A LOT OF IMAGES OF HARVEY MILK AND BECAUSE HE IS A
HERO TO THE COMMUNITY THAT IS RIGHT BUT WITH THAT COMES A
LITTLE BIT OF THE ICONOGRAPHY THAT SOMETIMES THESE PEOPLE
BECOME FLAT ICONS AND WE FORGET WHY THEY ARE ICONS AND WHY THEY
ARE HEROES AND THE LEGACY FOR THE CASTRO LGBTQ CULTURAL
DISTRICT OF HARVEY MILK LIES IN HIS ABILITY TO CREATE
COALITIONS AND IT WAS REALLY THE WORK OF HARVEY AND HOWARD
AND ANDY AND ALAN THAT CREATED THIS COALITION AND AN UNLIKELY
COALITION AT THAT THE CONNECTION BETWEEN LABOR
AND THE LGBT LGBTQ COMMUNITY WAS NOT A NATURAL ONE ALTHOUGH
IT BECAME ABUNDANTLY CLEAR TO ALL THOSE INVOLVED HOW NATURAL
IT TRULY WAS BECAUSE WE WERE FIGHTING FOR THE VERY SAME
THINGS FOR THE VERY SAME RIGHTS AND THE VERY SAME PROTECTIONS
AND THAT IS WHY IT'S IMPORTANT THAT THE CITY RECOGNIZE IT NOW
BECAUSE WE ARE STILL FIGHTING FOR THOSE THINGS.
WE ARE STILL BEING TARGETED WORKERS AND ORGANIZED LABOR ARE
BEING TARGETED IN THIS COUNTRY AS ARE LGBTQ PEOPLE.
EVEN HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO THIS BUDGET SERVES TO CUT OUR MOST
VULNERABLE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THIS IS WHY THIS RESOLUTION IS IMPORTANT.
THIS IS WHY THIS LEGISLATION IS IMPORTANT AND THIS IS WHY THIS
FIGHT TOGETHER, THIS COALITION TOGETHER AND SOLIDAIRE ITY IS
IMPORTANT. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME.
YES DISPLAY PLEASE AS OF GOV TV ON THE PROJECTOR THANK YOU ON
THE PROJECTOR PLEASE IT'S OH OKAY.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. NO INTRODUCTION SPEAKING TO THE
RESIDENTS DIRECTLY IN FRONT OF ME IN SAN FRANCISCO.
GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS ERIC MORGAN.
IN CASE YOU'RE WONDERING, I WENT TO SAINT IGNATIUS IF
ANYBODY CARES TO CHECK MY CREDENTIALS.
NONETHELESS, STRAIGHT TO BUSINESS.
YOUR BOARD IS CHECKED OUT, LADIES MANDELMAN.
THEY'RE ON THEIR PHONES. THEY'RE TEXTING.
THEY ARE NOT PAYING ATTENTION. SO LET ME RAISE THE STAKES
REALLY QUICKLY. WHAT YOU HAVE BEFORE YOU I'M
ALLEGING FRAUD, CONSPIRACY AND CORRUPTION IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. YOU GUYS CAN STAY CHECKED OUT
BILAL AND STEPHEN GOVERNMENT AUDIT YOUR COMMENTS TO THE
BOARD AS A WHOLE SEARCH OKAY SO THE BOARD AS A WHOLE IS LISTED
ON THIS EMAIL. >> CAN YOU CAN YOU PUT THAT
BACK UP PLEASE? THANK YOU.
THE BOARD IS LISTED ON THIS EMAIL.
PLEASE TAKE SCREENSHOTS. DO NOT UNDERESTIMATE WHAT I AM
BRINGING TO THE TABLE. >> SO THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE, THE DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN RESOURCES, THE SAN FRANCISCO
AIRPORT COMMISSION YOU FOLKS ON THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ON
THIS EMAIL TAKE THE DATES DOWN, DO YOUR RESEARCH.
I'M NOT TELLING YOU WHAT'S IN HERE BUT I AM PURPORTING
OKAY. SYSTEMIC FRAUD, CORRUPTION
AND CONSPIRACY. TRY ME.
I WILL BE HERE NEXT WEEK. CONTACT THE FOLKS THAT YOU NEED
TO PLEASE CHECK INTO IT. DO NOT TAKE THIS LIGHTLY.
>> OKAY. SO YOU'RE ON NOTICE.
BILAL STEPHEN YOU GUYS CAN KEEP LOOKING AT YOUR COMPUTERS BUT
YOU'RE ON NOTICE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. JUST MAKE SURE YOU'RE
ADDRESSING YOUR COMMENTS TO THE BOARD AS A WHOLE.
SIR. >> THANK YOU KINDLY.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> OKAY, EILEEN BOGAN I'M THE
PRESIDENT OF SPEAK AND SAID PARKSIDE EDUCATION IN ACTION
COMMITTEE I'M HERE ABOUT AGENDA ITEM NUMBER 15 TRIBUTE TO
CATHERINE MOORE, THE VICE PRESIDENT OF THE PLANNING
COMMISSION. >> I WILL KEEP IT VERY SIMPLE
TO COMMISSIONER VICE PRESIDENT MOORE, THANK YOU FOR CARING
ABOUT THE COASTAL ZONE ISSUE. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AGAIN
AND AGAIN IN OUR CITY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ARE NOT PAYING
ATTENTION TO DISMISSAL CLASS WHERE MANAGEMENT GANGS UPON
BONDS EMPLOY THESE WHO GET TRAUMATIZED AND MANY OF THEM
HAVE COMMITTED SUICIDE AND WE COME HERE AND WE TALK AND WHEN
WE COME HERE WE SEE ALL, YOU KNOW, CATERING TO WHATEVER.
BUT WHERE ARE THE STANDARDS THIS IS SAN FRANCISCO.
WE HAD STANDARDS. WE HAVE NO STANDARDS WHATSOEVER
. NOBODY CHALLENGES THE CIVIL
SERVICE COMMISSION. >> NOBODY CHALLENGES THE ASSET
BE YOU SEE THAT STARTED WITH $6 BILLION HAS NOW SPENT $15
BILLION AND IS HEADING TOWARDS $25 BILLION.
>> SO WHAT THE ARE Y'ALL DOING ?
>> BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND HISTORY EMPLOYEES THAT HAVE
FIRED WHO ARE TRAUMATIZED. >> YES, RIGHT INTO THE HOSPITAL
AND MONTHS LATER I HAD TO TAKE ON THE CASE AND OPEN UP THE
CASE WITH TORTURE AND I'M SICK SITTING IN THAT.
AM I SUPPOSED TO DO THAT? DO YOU KNOW MY AGE?
DO YOU KNOW FOR HOW LONG I'VE BEEN COMING HERE?
THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS TO HAVE TO COME WITH A PLAN TO
SERVE SAN FRANCISCANS. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT WEEK.
MY NAME IS JIM MCCARTHY. THANK YOU.
MEMBERS OF THE BOARD FOR HEARING ME.
I BELIEVE THAT THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO VOTED FOR AN
INSPECTOR GENERAL BECAUSE THE WHISTLEBLOWER PROGRAM WASN'T
DOING THAT GOOD OF A JOB TAKING CARE OF CORRUPTION IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> SO HERE ARE JADED, JADED
JUNE 23RD, 2026 HOW CAN I REPORT FRAUD, WASTE OR ABUSE TO
THE INSPECTOR GENERAL? THE INSPECTOR GENERALS
DEVELOPING STANDARDS AND PROCEDURES FOR RECEIVING
INFORMATION AND INITIATING INVESTIGATIONS?
IT'S BEEN SIX MONTHS. >> THEY HAVEN'T DONE IT YET.
THE IG CAN BE REACHED AT THE INSPECTOR GENERAL STANDARD OR
YOU COULD REACH HIM BUT THAT'S NOT WHERE YOU REPORT FRAUD TO
THE INSPECTOR GENERAL. IT'S NOT IN FACT YOU DON'T
REPORT FRAUD TO THE INSPECTOR GENERAL.
>> REPORTS OF FRAUD, WASTE AND ABUSE CAN BE MADE THROUGH
THE WHISTLEBLOWER PROGRAM SO THE INSPECTOR GENERAL IS UNDER
THE SAME CONFIDENTIALITY CLAUSE THAT THE WHISTLEBLOWER PROGRAM
IS IS JUST ANOTHER LEVEL ON TOP OF THE WHISTLEBLOWER PROGRAM WE
HAVE AN IG THAT'S BEING PAID AND POSSIBLY TWO OTHER PEOPLE
STILL THING HAPPENING HERE THE WHISTLEBLOWER PROGRAM THIS WORD
CORRUPTION GOES TO BE HIDDEN WHERE IT GOES TO DIE, WHERE IT
GOES TO FADE AWAY AND NOW THE IG IS FINALLY TO THAT OKAY
OKAY. >> CLAIRE AT THE COMPTROLLER'S
OFFICE TOLD ME I MAY NEVER BE ABLE TO FIND OUT WHAT THE
STANDARDS AND PROCEDURES ARE THAT MAY NEVER BE PUBLIC.
THAT'S SUNSHINE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> ANOTHER LEVEL OF PRO OCRACY THAT'S JUST GOING TO HIDE
CORRUPTION THROUGH A CONFIDENTIALITY CLAUSE THAT
FORBIDDEN FROM REVEALING ANYTHING THEY FIND OUT ABOUT.
>> THANK YOU. THANKS A LOT FOR THAT.
>> THAT'S GOING TO HELP FIGHT CORRUPTION.
SAN FRANCISCO PEACE AND LOVE. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER AND IF THERE ARE ANY OTHER
MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD
DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT, PLEASE STEP UP OTHERWISE THIS
WILL BE OUR LAST SPEAKER BUT COMPUTER TO MA'AM I CANNOT HEAR
YOU. MY APOLOGIES.
I'M SORRY CAN I USE THE COMPUTER TO ACCESS MY WEBSITE?
>> YOU CERTAINLY CAN. OKAY.
YOU'VE LOADED IT IN ADVANCE. >> OH NO.
YOU JUST GOT TO USE GOOGLE CHROME.
IS THAT IS THAT OKAY? WE'RE GOING TO HAVE SOMEONE
COME OVER TO YOU TO ASSIST YOU .
OKAY. THANK YOU.
I PRAY THERE'S SOMETHING YOU CAN DO RELATIVELY QUICKLY,
MA'AM. >> YEAH, IT'S JUST GOING TO
SHOW MY WEBSITE AND STREAMLINES IT SO I CAN TELL YOU THE
INFORMATION RIGHT NOW IF YOU NEED IT.
>> I'M GOING FORWARD. WE JUST ASK THAT YOU LOAD YOUR
INFORMATION. OH, HERE IT IS VERY QUICKLY SO
THAT WE CAN TAKE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS BEHIND YOU.
I DON'T SEE ANYONE IN LINE NOW BUT THEY'RE VERY WELL COULD BE
OKAY. >> THANK YOU.
I APPRECIATE IT. SO THIS WEBSITE STREAM LINES
I'M SETTING THE TIMER NOW. >> OKAY GREAT.
AND WAIT CAN YOU POSITIVE FOR A MINUTE LET ME JUST GET THE
WEBSITE UP AND TAKE YOUR TIME. HOW MUCH MORE TIME DO YOU THINK
YOU NEED, MA'AM? I GOT THIS.
ALL RIGHT. I WILL RESUME YOUR TIME.
>> YOU HAVE A MINUTE? 50 LEFT.
ALL RIGHT. >> SO THIS WEBSITE I JUST WANT
TO KNOW WHAT THE BOARD THINKS ABOUT THIS WEBSITE AND IF WE
COULD TRY TO USE IT. OKAY.
I HAVE BOARDED I ON THE PHONE WITH ME.
OKAY. IT'S GOV CENTRAL AND IT'S A
STATEWIDE SINGAPORE PORTAL FOR DIFFERENT GOVERNMENT SERVICES.
OKAY. AND IT HAS A LOT OF THE FORMS
THAT WE NEED ON HERE CASE ANYBODY NEEDS IT AND THEN IT
SHOWS THE DIFFERENT BUDGETS. >> I WANT TO SEE IF WE CAN HAVE
OUR BOARD LOOK INTO HOW ACCURATE THIS INFORMATION IS
AND IF ANYONE OUT THERE IS LISTENING THEY CAN WRITE
COMMENTS ABOUT ANYTHING. THERE'S ALSO OPPORTUNITIES FOR
PEOPLE TO YOU KNOW, GET A JOB. THERE'S ALSO A SECTION ABOUT,
YOU KNOW, SAN FRANCISCO AND SO I WANT TO SEE IF SOME OF THESE
SECTIONS ARE ACCURATE IF WE COULD WORK TOGETHER, IF WE CAN
HAVE THE BOARD HELP ME OUT AND KIND OF DECIDE WHETHER
THESE THE SECTIONS ARE ACCURATE.
>> I WAS TRYING TO GET A HOLD OF THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION
TO FIGURE OUT HOW TO DO THE REPARATIONS FUND.
>> IT'S BEEN KIND OF CHALLENGING.
I KNOW THAT THERE IS A REPARATIONS FUND THAT WAS
ESTABLISHED ON DECEMBER 23RD, 2025 BUT WE HAVEN'T SET UP A
PORTAL FOR IT YET. SO I'M TRYING TO FIGURE OUT HOW
TO CONTACT THEM BECAUSE THE LAST MEETING OR TOMORROW'S
MEETING IS CANCELED. SO I HAVE TO GIVE THEM THANK
YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS, MA'AM. ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT,
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 14
AND 15 TOGETHER. >> YES.
THESE ITEMS WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF EITHER OF THESE RESOLUTIONS ON FIRST READING
TODAY ANY MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO
GO TO COMMITTEE ITEM 14 THIS RESOLUTION.
>> WELL I MR. PRESIDENT AND I THINK ARE YOU TAKING THEM
INDIVIDUALLY OR PRESENTING THEM TOGETHER?
YES. YEAH.
>> AND SO ITEM 14 HONORS MARY CERVANTES FOR HER 100TH
BIRTHDAY AND ITEM 15 COMMENDING PLANNING COMMISSION VICE
PRESIDENT CATHERINE MOORE COULD YOU PLEASE CALL WHAT'S GOING ON
AND THERE'S A SUPERVISOR JIM COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON THESE ITEMS? >> YES ON ITEMS 14 AND 15
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT
MANDEL MEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUDER
SOLDER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
I HAVE NONE TO REPORT MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU PLEASE
READ THE IN MEMORIAM? >> YESTERDAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF PRESIDENT MANDEL MEN FOR THE LATE MR. JOHN V
GIUSTI ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR SAUDER FOR THE LATE MR..
FOR THE LATE MRS. JEANETTE ETHERIDGE ON BEHALF OF
SUPERVISORS CHERYL AND PRESIDENT MANDEL MEN FOR
THE LATE MS. NAGAR GAURI DEBBIE COCA.
>> AND ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AT THE
REQUEST OF SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR THE LATE MISS JULIE
DRISCOLL FARAH. >> MADAM CLERK, I THINK THAT
BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER
BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED